<?xml version='1.0' encoding='utf-8'?>
<container xmlns="https://open.law/schemas/library" xmlns:cache="https://open.law/schemas/cache" xmlns:citations="https://open.law/schemas/citations" xmlns:macro="https://open.law/schemas/macro" xmlns:xs="http://www.w3.org/2001/XMLSchema" xmlns:xsl="http://www.w3.org/1999/XSL/Transform" xmlns:codified="https://open.law/schemas/codified" xmlns:codify="https://open.law/schemas/codify" xmlns:xi="http://www.w3.org/2001/XInclude" containing-doc="San Mateo County, Cal., Ordinance Code">
  <prefix>Title</prefix>
  <num>3</num>
  <heading>PUBLIC SAFETY, MORALS AND WELFARE</heading>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.04</num>
    <heading>JUVENILE CURFEW REGULATIONS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.04.010</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite>, the following words and phrases shall be construed as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Youth" means any person under the age of 18 and is synonymous with the term "juvenile" for the purposes of <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Curfew hours" means the hours between 11:00 p.m. and 5:00 a.m. on Sunday through Thursday night and between 12:00 midnight and 5:00 a.m. on Friday and Saturday night, and between 8:30 a.m. and 1:30 p.m. on days when the school in which the student is registered is in session, or, in the case of juveniles who are not currently registered in school, when schools in the district in which the juvenile resides are in session.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Parent" means a person who is the birth parent, adoptive parent or stepparent of another person.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Guardian" means:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A person who, under court order, is the guardian of the person of a youth; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A public or private agency with whom a youth has been placed by a court; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A person who is at least 18 years of age and authorized by a parent or guardian to have the care and custody of a youth.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Emergency" means an unforeseen combination of circumstances that calls for immediate action. The term includes, but is not limited to, a fire, a natural disaster, an automobile accident, or any situation requiring immediate action to prevent serious bodily injury or loss of life.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"Public place" means any place to which the public or a substantial group of the public has access and includes, but is not limited to, streets, sidewalks, driveways, highways, private residences left open to the public without the presence of adult supervisors and the common areas of schools, hospitals, apartments, office buildings, parks, playgrounds, vacant lots and transportation facilities.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"Loiter" means to stand idly about or linger aimlessly.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>"Remain" means to linger or stay or to fail to leave a public place when requested to do so by a police officer of the person in control of the public place.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3699">Ord. 3699, 1/23/96</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4000">Ord. 4000, 10/17/00</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.04.020</num>
      <heading>Prohibited activities.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>It shall be unlawful for a youth to loiter or remain in any public place during curfew hours.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>It shall be unlawful for a parent or guardian of a youth knowingly to permit, or by insufficient control to allow, the youth to loiter or remain in any public place during curfew hours.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3699">Ord. 3699, 1/23/96</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.04.030</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text>The activities prohibited by <cite path="3.04.020">section 3.04.020</cite> shall not be unlawful in the following circumstances:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When the youth is accompanied by the youth's parent or guardian;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When the youth is on an errand at the direction of the youth's parent or guardian, without any detour or stop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>When the youth is in a motor vehicle involved in interstate travel or other travel not in violation of <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite>;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>When the youth is engaged in an employment activity, or is going to or returning home from an employment activity without any detour or stop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>When the youth is involved in an emergency;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>When the youth is attending an official school, religious, recreational, educational, social or other organized activity sponsored by a City, County, School, District or other similar private civic organization which supervises the activity, or when the youth is going to or returning home from such an activity without any detour or stop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>When the youth is going to or returning home from a private residence at which the youth was invited without any detour or stop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>When the youth is engaged in a commercial activity or receiving commercial services on the premises of a business organization that supervises and permits the activity, or when a youth is going to or returning home from such activity or service without any detour or stop;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>When the youth is married or has been emancipated according to California Family Code section 7000, et seq.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3699">Ord. 3699, 1/23/96</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.04.040</num>
      <heading>Enforcement procedure.</heading>
      <text>Before taking any enforcement action under <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite>, a Sheriff's Deputy or other law enforcement officer shall ask the apparent offender's age and reason for being in a public place during curfew hours. The officer shall not act to enforce <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite> unless the officer reasonably believes that an offense has occurred as provided in <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <text>Whenever a youth is apprehended for violation of <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite>, he or she shall be taken forthwith to a specified drop-off center and detained there while his or her parent or guardian is contacted. While at the drop-off center, the youth will be evaluated by the arresting officer with regard to apparent drug or alcohol abuse or other social service needs and referred to appropriate social services.</text>
      <text>Upon the second violation of <cite path="3.04">this chapter</cite> within one year, the Sheriff's Deputy or law enforcement officer shall be authorized to cite the youth and/or his or her parents or guardians and to refer the youth to Juvenile Probation.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3699">Ord. 3699, 1/23/96</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.05</num>
    <heading>PROHIBITION OF LOUD OR UNRULY GATHERINGS WHERE ANY ALCOHOL, ALCOHOLIC BEVERAGE, CANNABIS, AND/OR CONTROLLED SUBSTANCES ARE SERVED TO, INGESTED BY, OR IN THE POSSESSION OF MINORS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.010</num>
      <heading>Application of Chapter.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite> shall apply within the unincorporated area of San Mateo County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.020</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite>, the following words and phrases shall be construed as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Alcohol" and "Alcoholic Beverage" include any form of ethyl alcohol, from whatever source or by whatever process produced, spirits, liquor, wine, beer, and every liquid or solid containing such, and which contains one-half of one percent or more alcohol by volume and which is fit for beverage purposes either alone or when diluted, mixed, or combined with other substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Cannabis" means "cannabis", "cannabis product" and/or "cannabis concentrate", as defined in <cite path="5.14">Chapter 5.14</cite>8 of this ordinance code. For the purposes of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite>, the term "cannabis" does not include medical cannabis for which the person in possession has a valid recommendation for medical cannabis from a licensed medical care provider or a State of California medical cannabis I.D. card.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Controlled Substance" means a drug or substance whose possession and use are regulated under the California Controlled Substances Act (California Health and Safety Code Section 11000 et seq.). Such term does not include any drug or substance for which the individual found to have consumed or possessed such substance has a valid prescription issued by a licensed medical practitioner authorized to issue such a prescription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Costs for Public Safety Response Services" means the costs associated with responses by law enforcement or fire agencies to a gathering held in violation of this ordinance, including but not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The portion of the cost of salaries of the police officers and/or fire agency personnel, at the salary then in effect for each classification of each individual officer, for the actual amount of time spent responding to or remaining at the property where the disturbance was created, beginning when police officer or fire department personnel leaves a location to go to the scene of the event and ending when responding personnel are available for other duties, or, if their shifts are ended, when they are finished with those duties related to the event which they are required to complete before going off duty, or a minimum of one hour of time, whichever is greater. Such actual costs shall include wages and fringe benefits for the responding personnel and the sergeant or other superior directing them, including overtime if applicable; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The cost of repairing, or replacing if necessary, any County or fire agency equipment or property damaged as a result of the response by law enforcement or fire agency to the gathering.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Loud or Unruly Gathering" means a party or gathering of four (4) or more persons at any public or private premises, including a party bus or limousine, upon which loud or unruly conduct occurs. Such loud or unruly conduct constitutes a public nuisance and includes the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Excessive noise which violates any applicable ordinance;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Obstruction of public streets and/or the presence of unruly crowds that have spilled into public streets;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Public drunkenness or unlawful public consumption of alcohol, alcoholic beverages, cannabis, and/or controlled substances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(4)</num>
          <text>Assaults, batteries, fights, domestic violence or other disturbances of the peace;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(5)</num>
          <text>Vandalism;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(6)</num>
          <text>Litter; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(7)</num>
          <text>Any other conduct which constitutes a threat to the public health, safety, or quiet enjoyment of residential property or the general welfare.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"Minor" means any person less than twenty-one (21) years of age.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"Responsible Person" or "Social Host" means and includes, but is not limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A person who owns, rents, leases, or otherwise has control of the premises where the gathering occurs; and/or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A person who organized the event.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.030</num>
      <heading>Obligations of Social Host.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall act as a Social Host, as defined in <cite path="3.05.020">Section 3.05.020</cite> of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite>, of a Loud or Unruly Gathering where a Minor has possessed, consumed, or has been served any Alcohol, Alcoholic Beverage, Cannabis, and/or Controlled Substances.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>It is the duty of any Responsible Person who knowingly hosts, permits, or allows a gathering at any public or private premises to take all reasonable steps to prevent the possession and/or consumption of any Alcohol, Alcoholic Beverage, Cannabis and/or Controlled Substance by any Minor, as well as the service of these items to any Minor.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>As used in this section, reasonable steps shall mean and include, but shall not be limited to:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Controlling access to Alcohol, Alcoholic Beverages, Cannabis and/or Controlled Substances;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Verifying the age of persons at the gathering by inspecting government-issued driver's licenses or identification cards; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>Supervising the activities of Minors at the gathering.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.040</num>
      <heading>Public Nuisance.</heading>
      <text>Any gathering in violation of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite> is a public nuisance and an immediate danger to public health and safety. A violation is subject to any and all applicable civil, administrative, and criminal remedies and penalties according to the provisions and procedures contained in this ordinance code and state law including, but not limited to, an abatement action. All remedies provided herein shall be cumulative and not exclusive.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.050</num>
      <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The San Mateo County Sheriff or designee, may enforce <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A violation of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite> is punishable by administrative fines as set forth in <cite path="1.40">Chapter 1.40</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>In addition, a third or subsequent violation will result in liability on the part of the social host(s) for Costs for Public Safety Response Services as defined in <cite path="3.05.020">Section 3.05.020</cite> of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite>. All responsible parties will be held jointly and severally liable for these costs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>All fines and Costs for Public Safety Response Services shall be paid to the County within fourteen (14) days from the date of the citation or the notice of costs to be reimbursed under this ordinance.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text><cite path="3.05">This chapter</cite> shall not be interpreted to limit the applicable civil or administrative remedies available under law. All available enforcement procedures and remedies remain applicable including, but not limited to, administrative fines set forth in <cite path="1.40">Chapter 1.40</cite> of this ordinance code or other applicable law.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.060</num>
      <heading>Emergency Medical Assistance Exception.</heading>
      <text>No citation may be issued or any other enforcement action taken for violation of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite> if law enforcement is dispatched to the gathering because a Social Host or other participant at the gathering sought medical assistance on behalf of any person present. This section should be interpreted consistent with its purpose—to encourage social hosts and participants of gatherings to seek medical assistance whenever they believe it is needed, without fear of the consequences of violating the Ordinance.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.070</num>
      <heading>No Conflict with Federal or State Law.</heading>
      <text>Nothing in <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite> shall be interpreted or applied so as to create any requirement, power, or duty that is preempted by federal or state law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.05.080</num>
      <heading>Severability.</heading>
      <text>If any provision, section, subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, or word of this <cite path="3.05">Chapter 3.05</cite>, or any application thereof to any person or circumstance, is held to be invalid or unconstitutional by a court of competent jurisdiction, such decision shall not affect the validity of the remaining portions or applications of the chapter. The Board of Supervisors hereby declares that it would have passed <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite>, and each provision, section, subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, and word not declared invalid or unconstitutional without regard to whether any portion of <cite path="3.05">this chapter</cite> or application thereof would be subsequently declared invalid or unconstitutional.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04810" path="§1">Ord. No. 04810, § 1, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.08</num>
    <heading>INTOXICATION</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.08.010</num>
      <heading>Intoxication in public places prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any intoxicated persons or any person in an intoxicated or drunken condition to be in or on any public highway, road, street, sidewalk, lane, alley, public grounds, public park, public place, or place open to the public, or open to public view, or store, railroad depot, stadium, theater, or other place to which the public is admitted or invited.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3120</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 214">Ord. 214, 07/08/1907</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1060">Ord. 1060, 05/18/54</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.08.020</num>
      <heading>Intoxication in private premises to annoyance of others prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It is unlawful for any intoxicated person or any person in an intoxicated or drunken condition to be in any private house or in or on any private premises to the annoyance of any other person or persons.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3121</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 214">Ord. 214, 07/08/1907</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1060">Ord. 1060, 05/18/54</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.12</num>
    <heading>SOLICITING IN COUNTY COURTHOUSE</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.12.010</num>
      <heading>Soliciting prohibited.</heading>
      <text>Every person who shall, without the written approval of the County Manager or his duly authorized representative, upon any property owned or controlled by the County of San Mateo or within the grounds immediately surrounding such property, solicit any contributions for any purpose whatsoever, or who shall sell, offer for sale, or attempt to sell, any tickets, merchandise, chances, or lotteries or other things of value, shall be guilty of a misdemeanor.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3135</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 467">Ord. 467, 11/03/37</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2058">Ord. 2058, 06/16/70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.12.020</num>
      <heading>Exception.</heading>
      <text>It shall be permissible, however, for persons representing bona fide business firms to sell, offer for sale, and solicit orders for County supplies within the confines of said County property.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3136</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 467">Ord. 467, 11/03/37</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2058">Ord. 2058, 06/16/70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.16</num>
    <heading>SWITCH-BLADE KNIVES AND DANGEROUS WEAPONS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.16.010</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of <cite path="3.16">this chapter</cite>, certain terms, phrases and words shall be construed as follows:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Switch-Blade Knives" shall include, but shall not necessarily be limited to the following: all spring-blade knives, switch blade knives, snap-blade knives, or other similar knives of which any blade thereof, regardless of length, is released automatically by a spring mechanism or other mechanical device, or is released by any type of mechanism whatsoever.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Dangerous Weapon" shall include, but shall not necessarily be limited to the following: any knife with a blade three inches (3″) or more in length, any ice pick, awl, dirk, dagger, stiletto, or similar sharp stabbing tool, any straight-edged razor, razor blade fitted to a handle, razor with an unguarded blade, or any cutting, stabbing or bludgeoning weapon or device intended to be used as a club or capable of inflicting grievous bodily harm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Public Place" shall include but shall not necessarily be limited to the following: any public street, way, sidewalk, alley, public park, beach, recreational area, school, public building or place of public resort, any place where an athletic event, dance or other such gathering to which the public or a number thereof are admitted, and any place where alcoholic beverages are sold.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3140</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1196">Ord. 1196, 12/11/56</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.16.020</num>
      <heading>Sale or possession of switch-blade knives prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person shall sell, offer for sale, expose for sale, keep, carry, possess, loan, transfer, or give to any other person any switch-blade knife.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3141</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1196">Ord. 1196, 12/11/56</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.16.030</num>
      <heading>Possession of dangerous weapons in public places prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person having in his possession or immediate physical control, whether the same be concealed or visible, any dangerous weapon, to loaf or loiter upon any public place, or to wander about from place to place with no lawful business thereby to perform, or to hide, lurk or loiter upon or about the premises of another.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3142</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1196">Ord. 1196, 12/11/56</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.16.040</num>
      <heading>Possession prohibited continued—Public disorders.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person having within his possession or immediate physical control, whether the same be concealed or visible, any dangerous weapon, to engage in any fight or to participate in any riot, uprising or other type of disorderly conduct upon the premises of another or upon any public place.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3143</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1196">Ord. 1196, 12/11/56</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.16.050</num>
      <heading>Exception.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of sections <cite path="3.16.030">3.16.030</cite> and <cite path="3.16.040">3.16.040</cite> shall not be deemed to prohibit the possession or control of ordinary tools or equipment carried in good faith for the purpose of honest work, trade or business, or for use in a legitimate sport or recreation.</text>
      <text>Nothing in <cite path="3.16">this chapter</cite> shall prohibit police officers, special police officers, peace officers, or other law enforcement officers from carrying any wooden club, baton, or any equipment authorized by the properly constituted authorities for the enforcement of law in San Mateo County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3144</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1196">Ord. 1196, 12/11/56</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.20</num>
    <heading>GIVING OF FALSE INFORMATION</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.20.010</num>
      <heading>Giving of false information to any county agency or department is prohibited.</heading>
      <text>Any person, who knowingly makes any false, fictitious or fraudulent statement or representation to a County officer or employee in connection with any matter within the jurisdiction of any department or agency of the County, or who knowingly falsifies, conceals or covers up by direct scheme or device any fact, or makes or uses any false writing or document when he knows the same to contain any false, fictitious or fraudulent statement or entry, is guilty of a misdemeanor.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3160</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1336">Ord. 1336, 01/27/59</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">catchline editorially created, 6/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.24</num>
    <heading>CRAP GAMES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.24.010</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.24">this chapter</cite>, the phrase "public place" shall mean any public highway, road, street, sidewalk, lane, alley, open private grounds, or any structure open, other than through its doors or windows, to public view from public or adjoining private property.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3165</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1393">Ord. 1393, 04/26/60</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.24.020</num>
      <heading>Craps or variations thereof prohibited in public places.</heading>
      <text>No person shall engage or participate in playing of the game of craps or any variation thereof, for anything of value, in a public place.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3166</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1393">Ord. 1393, 04/26/60</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.24.030</num>
      <heading>Loitering in public places where game of craps or variations thereof being played.</heading>
      <text>No person, with knowledge of such game, shall loiter about a public place where persons are engaging or participating in the game of craps or any variation thereof, for anything of value.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3167</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1393">Ord. 1393, 04/26/60</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.24.040</num>
      <heading>Presumptions.</heading>
      <text>In a trial for violation of the provisions of <cite path="3.24.030">section 3.24.030</cite> of <cite path="3.24">this chapter</cite>, it should be presumed that any person has knowledge of such game who, for five or more minutes, is at or within ten feet of a public place where a game of craps or variation thereof, for anything of value, is participated or engaged in. This shall be a rebuttable presumption.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3168</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.28</num>
    <heading>PROSTITUTION AND LEWDNESS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.28.010</num>
      <heading>Distributing, selling, etc., of indecent and obscene matter prohibited.</heading>
      <text>Every person who knowingly writes, composes, stereotypes, prints, publishes, or otherwise prepares, or either offers or advertises to offer for gift or for sale, or sells, distributes, makes a gift of, or causes any person to carry, convey or transport, or exhibits any obscene or indecent writing, paper, or book; or designs, copies, draws, engraves, paints, or otherwise prepares or either offers or advertises to offer for gift or for sale, or sells, or makes a gift of, distributes or causes any person to carry, convey, or transport, or exhibits any obscene or indecent figure, picture, moving picture or other obscene and indecent image is guilty of a misdemeanor. The word "person" as used herein shall be deemed not to include a public officer, employee or agent of the United States Government or of the State of California or a political subdivision thereof, or of a local governmental agency who is acting within the course and scope of his employment or agency.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3170</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1387">Ord. 1387, 02/23/60</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.28.020</num>
      <heading>Prostitution defined.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.28">this chapter</cite> prostitution is defined as an act of sexual intercourse or a lewd act performed by a female person with a male person not married to her, and as a result of, or through the promise of, the exchange of money or article of value.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3175</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1441">Ord. 1441, 02/21/61</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3301">Ord. 3301, 03/12/91</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.28.030</num>
      <heading>Soliciting prostitution and lewd acts prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to solicit by word, act or any other form of communication, any person for the purpose of prostitution, or for the purpose of engaging in a lewd act between members of the same sex.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3176</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1441">Ord. 1441, 02/21/61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.28.040</num>
      <heading>Unlawful to offer or agree to commit prostitution or other lewd act.</heading>
      <text>Every person is guilty of a misdemeanor who:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Offers or agrees to commit, or commits, any act of prostitution; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Offers to secure another for the purpose of committing any act of prostitution, fornication, assignation or for any other lewd or indecent act with any other person; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Solicits another to lease, rent or otherwise make available a room, place or building to be used for the purpose of committing any lewd or indecent act or any act of prostitution; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Is in or near any thoroughfare or public place for the purpose of inducing, enticing or procuring another to commit an act of lewdness, fornication or unlawful sexual intercourse; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Knowingly transports any person to any place for the purpose of committing any lewd or indecent act or any act of prostitution; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Knowingly receives, offers or agrees to receive any person into any place or building for the purpose of assignation or of performing any act of lewdness or fornication, or knowingly permits any person to remain there for any such purposes; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Directs any person to any place for the purpose of committing any lewd or indecent act or any act of prostitution or fornication; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>In any way aids or abets or participates in the doing of any of the acts prohibited by subdivisions (a) to (g), inclusive, of this section.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3177</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1441">Ord. 1441, 02/21/61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.32</num>
    <heading>NUDITY</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.010</num>
      <heading>Legislative authorization.</heading>
      <text><cite path="3.32">This chapter</cite> is adopted pursuant to sections 318.5 and 318.6 of the Penal Code of the State of California. All words used in <cite path="3.32">this chapter</cite> which are also used in said sections 318.5 and 318.6 are used in the same sense and mean the same as the same respective words used in said sections 318.5 and 318.6 of the Penal Code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.020</num>
      <heading>Theater—Definition.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.32">this chapter</cite>, and in sections 318.5 and 318.6 of the Penal Code, the terms "theater", "concert hall", or "other similar establishment which is primarily devoted to theatrical performances" shall mean a building, playhouse, hall or other place having permanently affixed seats so arranged that a body of spectators can have an unobstructed view of the stage, upon which theatrical or vaudeville performances or similar forms of artistic expression are presented, and where such performances are not incidental to promoting the sale of food, drink or other merchandise, and for which a County license for a theater is in full force and effect. This definition does not supersede the provisions of <cite path="3.32.010">section 3.32.010</cite> of this code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.030</num>
      <heading>Prohibition against display of private parts.</heading>
      <text>Every person is guilty of a misdemeanor who exposes his or her private parts or buttocks, or employs any device or covering to simulate the private parts or pubic hair of such person, while participating in any live act, demonstration or exhibition in any public establishment, establishment open to the public, or establishment open to public view, or while serving food or drink or both to any customer.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.040</num>
      <heading>Accessories.</heading>
      <text>Every person is guilty of a misdemeanor who permits, procures, counsels, or assists any person to violate any provision of <cite path="3.32.030">section 3.32.030</cite> of this code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.050</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text><cite path="3.32">This chapter</cite> does not apply to:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>a theater, concert hall, or similar establishment which is primarily devoted to theatrical performances, or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>any act authorized or prohibited by any State statute.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178.4</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.060</num>
      <heading>Penalty.</heading>
      <text>A violation of <cite path="3.32">this chapter</cite> is punishable by a fine not exceeding five hundred dollars ($500) or by imprisonment in the County Jail for not more than six (6) months, or by both such fine and imprisonment.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178.5</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.32.070</num>
      <heading>Constitutionality.</heading>
      <text>If any provision or clause of <cite path="3.32">this chapter</cite>, or application thereof to any person or circumstance, is held invalid by a court of competent jurisdiction, such invalidity shall not affect any other provision or application of <cite path="3.32">this chapter</cite> which can be given effect without the invalid provision or application, and to this end the provisions of <cite path="3.32">this chapter</cite> are declared to be severable.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3178.6</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2208">Ord. 2208, 07/10/73</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.36</num>
    <heading>GAMBLING GAMES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.36.010</num>
      <heading>Certain gambling games prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person shall play any game of chance or skill with cards for money, check, credit or other representative of value in any public barroom or other public place, or place open to public view, or in any place where money or other valuable consideration is charged in any manner for the privilege of playing such games of chance or skill.</text>
      <text>This section shall not apply to any games made unlawful under the provisions of the Penal Code of the State of California.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3180</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1491">Ord. 1491, 12/12/61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.36.020</num>
      <heading>Gambling house, public place.</heading>
      <text>No person having possession, charge of, or control of any public barroom or public place shall permit, suffer, let or allow to be played therein for money, checks, credit or other representative of value, any game of chance or skill played with cards, which game is not made unlawful under the provisions of the Penal Code of the State of California.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3181</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1491">Ord. 1491, 12/12/61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.36.030</num>
      <heading>Gambling house, private place.</heading>
      <text>No person having possession, charge or control of any room, quarters, flat, apartment or any premises, shall charge any person or persons any sum of money or representative of value for the privilege of playing any game of chance or skill with cards not made unlawful under the provisions of the Penal Code of the State of California.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3182</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1491">Ord. 1491, 12/12/61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.40</num>
    <heading>INTERFERENCE WITH POLICE DOGS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.40.010</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.40">this chapter</cite>, the term "police dog" shall mean any dog specially trained for assistance to law enforcement officers, and which dog is under the control of a law enforcement officer in the performance of his duties.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3190</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1659">Ord. 1659, 07/14/64</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.40.020</num>
      <heading>Interference with police dog prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person shall injure, tease, strike or otherwise interfere with any police dog while said dog is in the custody of, or being used by, a law enforcement officer in the performance of his official duties.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3191</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1659">Ord. 1659, 07/14/64</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">catchline editorially created, 6/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.44</num>
    <heading>LOITERING AND PUBLIC DRINKING OF ALCOHOL</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.44.010</num>
      <heading>Consumption of alcoholic beverages near certain public places prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to consume any alcoholic beverage on any highway, street, alley, sidewalk, public parking lot, parking lot open to the public use or pedestrian walkway open to public use within one thousand (1000) feet of buildings or places open to the public where alcoholic beverages are sold. This section shall not be deemed to make punishable any act or acts which are prohibited by any law of the State of California.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3195.0</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2043">Ord. 2043, 05/12/70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.44.020</num>
      <heading>Loitering near certain places prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to loiter in, on or about buildings and places open to the public where alcoholic beverages are sold.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3195.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2043">Ord. 2043, 05/12/70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.44.030</num>
      <heading>Loitering defined.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.44">this chapter</cite>, "loiter" means to linger, wait, or delay in and about the places designated with no lawful purpose.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3195.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2043">Ord. 2043, 05/12/70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.44.040</num>
      <heading>Buildings and places where alcoholic beverages sold defined.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.44">this chapter</cite>, "buildings and places open to the public where alcoholic beverages are sold" means, but is not limited to, any liquor store, liquor outlet, inn, tavern, bar, saloon, or any premises wherein the owner, tenant or occupant possesses, and purveys alcoholic beverages to the public pursuant to, an "on sale" or "off sale" liquor license of whatever classification.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3195.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2043">Ord. 2043, 05/12/70</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.48</num>
    <heading>GRAFFITI</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.010</num>
      <heading>Purpose of chapter.</heading>
      <text>The purpose of <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite> is to provide a program for removal of graffiti in a timely manner from walls and structures on both public and private property in the unincorporated area San Mateo County and to provide regulation designed to prevent and control the further spread of graffiti in the unincorporated area of San Mateo County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3200</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3624">Ord. 3624, 1/24/95</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.020</num>
      <heading>Graffiti defined.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite>, "graffiti" shall mean any defacing of public or private buildings, structures or places, unauthorized by the owner or other person in control of the property, through any inscription, word, figure or design that is marked, etched, scratched, drawn or painted using application of paint, ink, chalk, dye or any other similar substance.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3201</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.030</num>
      <heading>Graffiti prohibited.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall place or cause to be placed graffiti upon any publicly or privately owned permanent building or structure within unincorporated area of San Mateo County.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person owning or otherwise in control of any real property within the unincorporated area of the County shall allow or permit any graffiti to remain on, for a period in excess of that prescribed by <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite> for notice and removal of graffiti, any permanent structure located on such property when the graffiti is visible from the street or other public or private property.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3202</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3624">Ord. 3624, 1/24/95</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.040</num>
      <heading>Notice and consent for removal of graffiti.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Whenever the Sheriff or designee, or the Director of Public Works or designee, determines that graffiti exists on any permanent structure in the unincorporated area of San Mateo County which is visible from the street or other public or private property, the Sheriff or Director shall cause a notice to be served on the property owner demanding abatement of the graffiti as provided by this section.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The notice shall be served on the owner(s) of the affected property, as such owner's name and address appear on the last equalized property tax assessment rolls of the County of San Mateo. The notice shall be served by either personal delivery or certified or first class mail. In addition, where the property is known to be occupied by other than the record owner, a copy of the notice shall be sent by certified or first class mail to the occupant at the property address or posted on the affected property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The notice shall inform the property owner that the graffiti exists and must be immediately abated. The notice shall request that, within ten days of personal delivery or mailing of the notice, the owner either abate the graffiti or sign and return a consent form authorizing the County to enter the property and abate the graffiti, at County expense, by cleaning, painting or otherwise removing the graffiti. The consent form to be signed by the owner shall be prepared by the County and served with the notice to abate.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>If the property owner consents to removal by the County, as provided by subsection (c) of this section, the Sheriff or the Director of Public Works may enter and abate the graffiti by County forces, volunteer labor, private contractor, or other means.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3203</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3624">Ord. 3624, 01/24/95</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4405">Ord. 4405, 01/08/08</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.050</num>
      <heading>Failure to remove graffiti or provide consent for removal by County.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In the event the property owner receiving notice under <cite path="3.48.030">section 3.48.030</cite> fails to either abate the graffiti or consent to abatement by the County, within the ten day period, the County may proceed to abate the graffiti under any applicable nuisance abatement procedure including, but not limited to, the nuisance abatement procedures provided in sections <cite path="1.12.010">1.12.010</cite> through <cite path="1.12.040">1.12.040</cite> of the San Mateo County Ordinance Code, to include assessment of the costs of abatement against the owner and placement of an abatement lien. If the County anticipates that these abatement procedures will be used, any notice required by <cite path="1.12.020">section 1.12.020</cite> of this Code may be included in the notice specified by <cite path="3.48.040">section 3.48.040</cite> so that only one ten day notice period is required prior to abatement by the County. County employees, agents and volunteer and other work crews supervised by the County and private contractors of the County are expressly authorized to enter private property for purposes of abating graffiti under any nuisance abatement procedure.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Where graffiti has been abated by the County due to the refusal or failure of the property owner to either remove the graffiti or to allow the County to remove the graffiti, the owner shall reimburse the County for the actual cost of the removal of the graffiti. If the statute or ordinance under which the County proceeds with abatement does not specify the costs to be included, such costs shall include labor, material, inspection and reasonable administrative costs.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3204</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.060</num>
      <heading>Removal of graffiti from public property.</heading>
      <text>Graffiti found on property owned by a public entity other than the County may be removed after securing consent from the public agency having jurisdiction over the structure or real property on which the graffiti is located. The costs for such removal shall be paid as agreed between the other public agency and the County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3205</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.070</num>
      <heading>Penalty for violation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any person found guilty of applying graffiti in violation of <cite path="3.48.030">section 3.48.030</cite>, shall reimburse the County or the property owner for any and all costs the owner or the County may incur in removing graffiti under <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite>. If the violator is a minor, the parent or guardian shall be responsible for such reimbursement. Such reimbursement shall be in addition to any other civil or criminal penalties authorized by law to be imposed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Any person who fails to comply with any order of abatement or who violates any other provision of <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite> is guilty of an infraction, punishable as set forth in <cite path="1.12.070">section 1.12.070</cite> of this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any person who obstructs, impedes or interferes with any representative of the County or any property owner when engaged in proceedings involving abatement of graffiti under <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite> is guilty of an infraction, punishable as set forth in <cite path="1.12.070">section 1.12.070</cite> of this Code.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3206</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.48.080</num>
      <heading>Remedies cumulative.</heading>
      <text>Nothing in <cite path="3.48">this chapter</cite> shall be deemed to prevent the County Counsel or District Attorney from commencing a civil or criminal proceeding or action to abate a public nuisance under any other applicable law. The remedies provided for herein shall be cumulative and not exclusive.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3207</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3515">Ord. 3515, 10/26/93</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3568">Ord. 3568, 05/10/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.50</num>
    <heading>ILLEGAL DUMPING AND LITTERING</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.010</num>
      <heading>Purposes.</heading>
      <text>The purpose and intent of <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> is to protect public and private property from illegal dumping by streamlining and enhancing the tools and remedies available to address and discourage such acts.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.020</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>The following terms are defined for use in <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>"Appliance" means a large electronic or gas appliance such as a stove, refrigerator, microwave, water heater, or furnace.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>"Commercial quantity" means any amount of waste matter generated in the course of a trade, business, profession, or occupation, or an amount of waste matter equal to or in excess of one cubic yard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>"Costs" means and includes, without limitation, court costs, attorneys' fees, costs of removal and disposal of illegally dumped waste matter, costs of investigating the incident and enforcing this <cite path="3.50">chapter 3.50</cite> with respect to an incident of illegal dumping or littering, and costs of identifying the person(s) who cause or commit illegal dumping or littering.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>"Electronic waste" means computers, computer monitors, tablets, televisions, audio equipment, video equipment, small appliances such as coffee makers, microwaves, vacuum cleaners and any other electronic equipment that is required to be specially disposed of pursuant to California state law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>E.</num>
        <text>"Harmful waste matter" means a hazardous substance as defined in section 374.8 of the California Penal Code and in <cite path="4.92">chapter 4.92</cite> of this code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>F.</num>
        <text>"Household furniture" means large furniture, such as a table, armoire, dresser, or similar sized furniture.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>G.</num>
        <text>"Illegal dumping" means the willful, intentional, or negligent depositing, dropping, dumping, placing, or throwing of any waste matter onto public or private property that is not expressly designated for the purpose of disposal of waste matter. Illegal dumping does not include littering as defined below.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>H.</num>
        <text>"Littering" means the willful, intentional, or negligent discarding onto public or private property of small quantities of waste matter related to consumer goods and that are reasonably understood to be ordinarily carried on or about the body of a living person, including, without limitation, beverage containers, packaging, wrappers, wastepaper, receipts, cardboard, newspaper, magazines, cigarette butts, used gum, or similar waste matter that escapes or is allowed to escape from a container, receptacle, or package.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>I.</num>
        <text>"Universal waste" means lamps, batteries, mercury-containing devices, and lighting ballasts.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>J.</num>
        <text>"Upholstered furniture" means furniture that is covered by soft, padded textile, leather, vinyl, or similar covering, such as couches, sofas, and armchairs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>K.</num>
        <text>"Waste matter" means any form of tangible matter including, without limitation, any of the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>All forms of garbage, refuse, trash, junk, debris, recyclable materials, and solid waste.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Dirt, rock, soil, gravel, sand, compost of any form, wood chips or mulch, tree debris, grass clippings, or other aggregate material dumped or deposited as refuse.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Abandoned or discarded furniture and children's toys and accessories.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Construction materials, machinery, structures, or containers.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>All forms of liquid waste not otherwise defined or deemed to fall within the purview of section 25117 of the California Health and Safety Code, including, without limitation, paints, chemical solutions, and contaminated water.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>Any form of biological waste not otherwise designated by law as hazardous waste.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.030</num>
      <heading>Illegal dumping and littering unlawful.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>It is unlawful and a violation of this code and <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> for any person to illegally dump waste matter, or to cause waste matter to be disposed of in a manner not otherwise authorized by this code or state or federal law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>It is unlawful and a violation of this code and <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> for any person owning or otherwise in possession or control of any real property within the County to permit or allow waste matter from such property to be illegally dumped.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>It is unlawful and a violation of this code and <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> for any person to litter or to cause littering.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>D.</num>
        <text>A violation of <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> shall be subject to enforcement through criminal prosecution, civil action, administrative citation, and civil penalties, as provided herein.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.040</num>
      <heading>Illegal dumping and littering are public nuisances.</heading>
      <text>The Board of Supervisors hereby declares and finds that illegal dumping and littering are each public nuisances subject to abatement, remedies, and penalties according to the provisions and procedures contained in this code and <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.050</num>
      <heading>Criminal penalties available for illegal dumping.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Illegal Dumping is a Misdemeanor. Illegal dumping is a misdemeanor violation of this code and <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite>, in addition to any California Penal Code violations and any administrative or civil penalties that may apply to such illegal dumping.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Littering is an Infraction. Littering is an infraction violation of this code and <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite>, in addition to any California Penal Code violations and any administrative or civil penalties that may apply to such littering.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.060</num>
      <heading>Administrative remedies for illegal dumping.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Administrative Citations. Except in cases of major violations, as defined below in this <cite path="3.50.060">section 3.50.060</cite>, illegal dumping and littering are subject to the administrative remedies set forth in <cite path="1.40">chapter 1.40</cite> of this code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Major Violations.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The following are considered major violations: (1) where the illegal dumping involves a commercial quantity, harmful waste matter, a mattress, tires, household furniture, upholstered furniture, an appliance, universal waste, or electronic waste; or (2) where a person receives more than three administrative citations within a one-year period, the next instance of illegal dumping by that person will be deemed a major violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>A person who commits a major violation shall be cited and given notice to remove the illegally dumped waste material from the public or private property. If the person found to commit a major violation fails to remove the illegally dumped waste material from the public or private property within 24 hours after receiving notice as specified below in <cite path="3.50.060|(B)|(3)">section 3.50.060(B)(3)</cite>, the person shall be subject to an administrative penalty of $3,000.00.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Notice of a major violation shall contain the following information: (a) the date of the major violation and any previous administrative citations for illegal dumping or littering issued within the preceding one-year period to the person receiving the notice of major violation; (b) a description of the illegally dumped waste material constituting the major violation; (c) the address or a definite description of where the major violation occurred; and (d) evidence identifying the person receiving the notice as the person responsible for the major violation. Notice of the major violation shall be provided by personal delivery to the person being notified.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Any person receiving notice of a major violation may request an appeal hearing pursuant to the process provided in <cite path="1.40">chapter 1.40</cite> of this code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Separate Violations. The following are considered separate instances of illegal dumping or littering, each of which is subject to the above remedies:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Each individual mattress, appliance, item of electronic waste, item of household furniture, item of upholstered furniture, item of universal waste, or item of harmful waste matter illegally dumped is a separate major violation. For example, illegally dumping both a mattress and an appliance would constitute two (2) separate major violations, each of which is subject to the above $3,000.00 administrative penalty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Each cubic yard of waste matter illegally dumped is a separate major violation. For example, illegally dumping two (2) cubic yards of waste matter would constitute two (2) separate major violations, each of which is subject to the above $3,000.00 administrative penalty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>A commercial quantity of waste matter illegally dumped which also contains harmful waste matter, a mattress, an appliance, upholstered furniture, household furniture, or electronic waste may be cited both as a commercial quantity and separately as harmful waste matter, a mattress, an appliance, universal waste, upholstered furniture, household furniture, or electronic waste, and each constitutes a separate major violation. For example, illegally dumping an appliance which measures more than a cubic yard would constitute two (2) separate major violations, each of which is subject to the above $3,000.00 administrative penalty.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Each individual act of illegal dumping or littering at the same location is a separate violation.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>Each day an act of illegal dumping or littering continues unabated is a separate violation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.070</num>
      <heading>Recovery of penalties.</heading>
      <text>The County may collect any past due administrative penalty by use of any and all available legal means, including, without limitation, as personal obligation or as a lien or special assessment recorded against any real property owned by the person(s) found to have committed an act of illegal dumping or littering.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.080</num>
      <heading>Civil remedies for illegal dumping and littering.</heading>
      <text>County Counsel may bring a civil action against any person found to have committed an act of illegal dumping or littering. In the civil action, County Counsel may pursue all available remedies authorized by law and may seek to recover all costs related to the illegal dumping or littering.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.090</num>
      <heading>Joint and several liability.</heading>
      <text>Each person who participates in an act of illegal dumping is jointly and severally liable with any other person who participates for all citations, major violations, fines, penalties, damages, and costs related to that act of illegal dumping.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.100</num>
      <heading>Liability of owner or operator of motor vehicle used in illegal dumping.</heading>
      <text>To the extent permitted by law, an owner or operator of a motor vehicle is liable and responsible for all citations, major violations, fines, penalties, damages, and costs related to an act of illegal dumping when the owner's vehicle is used in connection with any act of illegal dumping with the express or implied permission of the owner or operator.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.110</num>
      <heading>Responsibility of lessor for property of lessee illegally dumped following vacation of unit.</heading>
      <text>A real property owner who rents commercial or residential property is responsible for the property of a tenant which was removed from the tenant's unit and illegally dumped. If the tenant's property is removed from the tenant's unit by the real property owner, anyone acting on behalf of the property owner, or an eviction or other process, the property owner must ensure the tenant's property is either retained for the tenant or properly disposed of in accordance with law. If the tenant's property is illegally dumped in front of the tenant's former unit, adjacent properties, or the public right-away, the real property owner must ensure the tenant's property is properly disposed of in accordance with the law. If the tenant's property is illegally dumped at a different location, the real property owner must provide the tenant's forwarding information if it is within the real property owner's knowledge.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.120</num>
      <heading>Development of community service program in lieu of fine.</heading>
      <text>The County Manager is authorized to develop an illegal dumping and litter community service program to be offered for violators of <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> in lieu of payment of any citations, fines, penalties, and/or costs.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.50.130</num>
      <heading>Remedies cumulative.</heading>
      <text>The remedies provided for the enforcement of <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> are in addition to and do not supersede or limit any and all other remedies provided by law. The remedies provided in <cite path="3.50">this chapter</cite> are cumulative and not exclusive.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04756" path="§2">Ord. No. 04756, § 2, 5-10-2016</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.52</num>
    <heading>FIREARMS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.010</num>
      <heading>Definition of "firearms".</heading>
      <text>Firearms is defined as a cannon, gun, pistol, revolver, automatic pistol, rifle, shotgun, "BB" gun, air gun, pellet gun or any other weapon of similar nature designed to discharge a projectile propelled by the expansion of a gas.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3250.0</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1047">Ord. 1047, 03/02/54</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.020</num>
      <heading>Discharge of firearms prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person shall, within the unincorporated area of the County of San Mateo, discharge or fire any firearm, except as provided in <cite path="3.52.030">section 3.52.030</cite> hereof.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3250.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1047">Ord. 1047, 03/02/54</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.030</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="3.52.020">section 3.52.020</cite> as to the use of any firearm shall not apply to any of the following cases:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>To sheriffs, constables, marshals, policemen, or other peace officers, or any person summoned by any such officers to assist in making arrests or preserving the peace, or persons who are members of the armed services of the United States, or the National Guard, while such persons are acting in the lawful discharge of their duties;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>To persons using firearms in the lawful defense of self, third persons, or the user's property;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>To persons discharging or firing such firearms or causing them to be discharged or fired at a regularly established firing, shooting or target range with the consent of the owner and/or person in charge of any such firing, shooting or target range; the term "regularly established firing, shooting or target range" as used in this subsection includes properly constructed indoor and/or outdoor home ranges on private property when such range is supervised by an adult.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>To persons lawfully hunting pursuant to the provisions of the California Fish and Game Code.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3250.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1047">Ord. 1047, 03/02/54</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.040</num>
      <heading>Possession by minor prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person under the age of eighteen (18) years to have in his possession in a public place any firearm, except as provided in <cite path="3.52.050">section 3.52.050</cite> hereof.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3250.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1047">Ord. 1047, 03/02/54</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.050</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="3.52.040">section 3.52.040</cite> hereof shall not apply to said persons under the age of eighteen (18) in the following cases:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>When said person is in the immediate charge of a parent, guardian, or adult person having the responsibility for the conduct of said person under the age of eighteen (18) years.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When the firearm is unloaded and either: (1) in a dismantled or "take-down" condition or (2) completely wrapped or in a carrying case made for the purpose of carrying such firearm. A gun shall be deemed to be unloaded only when no ammunition or propellant is in any part of the gun or magazine or clip thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>When said person is lawfully hunting pursuant to the provisions of the California Fish and Game Code and in possession of a hunting license issued as prescribed by that code.</text>
      </para>
      <text>Any person violating any of the provisions of this ordinance shall be deemed guilty of a misdemeanor and upon conviction thereof shall be punished by a fine not exceeding the sum of Five Hundred Dollars ($500.00) or by imprisonment in the County Jail of San Mateo County, for a period not exceeding six months, or by both such fine and imprisonment.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3250.4</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1047">Ord. 1047, 03/02/54</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.060</num>
      <heading>Sale of certain firearms prohibited to minors.</heading>
      <text>No person shall sell, deliver or transfer ownership to any person under the age of eighteen (18) years any pistol, revolver or other similar weapon capable of being concealed upon the person and designed to discharge a solid projectile propelled by the expansion of a gas.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3250.5</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1315">Ord. 1315, 08/19/58</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.070</num>
      <heading>Adoption of Penal Code Sections 12070 through 12077.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of sections 12070-12077, inclusive, of the Penal Code of the State of California, pertaining to the licensing of retailers selling pistols, revolvers, and other firearms capable of being concealed upon the person, are hereby adopted in the County of San Mateo and from and after the effective date of this ordinance shall be in full force and effect in this County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3255.0</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1141">Ord. 1141, 11/15/55</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">catchline editorially created, 6/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.080</num>
      <heading>Sheriff—Duties.</heading>
      <text>The Sheriff of San Mateo County is hereby designated and appointed the duly constituted licensing authority of this County for the purpose of this ordinance. All applications for licenses under the foregoing Penal Code sections shall be made to the Sheriff and he is hereby authorized to grant licenses, effective for one year from the date of issue, to enforce within the unincorporated area of this County the provisions of sections 12070-12077 of said Penal Code, and to obtain and, where necessary, to prescribe forms effectuate the purposes of said sections and to otherwise do all acts and things required to make effective and to enforce within this County the provisions of sections 12070-12077 of the California Penal Code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3255.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1141">Ord. 1141, 11/15/55</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">catchline editorially created, 6/94</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.090</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>The following definitions govern the construction of <cite path="3.52">this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Firearm" shall mean any device, designed to be used as a weapon or modified to be used as a weapon, that expels a projectile by the force of an explosion or other form of combustion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Firearm ammunition" shall mean any cartridge or encasement containing a bullet or projectile, propellant or explosive charge, and a primer which is used in the operation of a firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Firearm ammunition component" shall mean any cartridge or encasement, bullet or projectile, primer or propellant or explosive material used in the manufacture of ammunition.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3735">Ord. 3735, 9/24/96</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4078">Ord. 4078, 11/06/01</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.110</num>
      <heading>Licenses—Conditions.</heading>
      <text>Licensees shall be subject to the following conditions, for breach of any of which the license shall be subject to forfeiture:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(1)</num>
        <text>The business shall be carried on only in the building designated in the license.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(2)</num>
        <text>The license or a copy thereof, certified by the issuing authority, shall be displayed on the premises where it can easily be read.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(3)</num>
        <text>No pistol or revolver shall be delivered:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(a)</num>
          <text>Within three days of the application for the purchase, and when delivered shall be unloaded and securely wrapped; nor</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(b)</num>
          <text>Unless the purchaser either is personally known to the seller or shall present clear evidence of his identity.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(4)</num>
        <text>No pistol or revolver, or imitation thereof, or placard advertising the sale or other transfer thereof, shall be displayed in any part of the premises where it can readily be seen from the outside.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(5)</num>
        <text>Deleted.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(6)</num>
        <text>The licensee shall not deliver a firearm to a purchaser, lessee or other transferee unless the firearm is unloaded and securely wrapped or unloaded in a locked container.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(7)</num>
        <text>The licensee shall not sell, lease or otherwise transfer a firearm without also selling or otherwise providing with each firearm a trigger lock or similar device that is designed to prevent the unintentional discharge of the firearm.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3255.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1141">Ord. 1141, 11/15/55</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">catchline editorially created, 6/94</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3735">Ord. 3735, 9/24/96</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4078">Ord. 4078, 11/06/01</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.120</num>
      <heading>Copies of register sheet, disposition of.</heading>
      <text>Licensees shall, immediately upon receiving an application for purchase, mail a copy of the register sheet required to be maintained to the Bureau of Criminal Identification and Investigation and to the Sheriff, as required by Penal Code section 12076. The Sheriff shall, upon receiving said copy, investigate and report to said retailer whether or not the purchaser is known to be a minor under the age of eighteen (18) years or within one of the classes of persons prohibited by section 12021 of said Penal Code from owning or possessing such weapon. Such persons are narcotics addicts, persons convicted of felonies and persons not citizens of the United States.</text>
      <text>If any section, provision, sentence, clause or phrase of this ordinance is for any reason held to be invalid or unconstitutional, such invalidity or unconstitutionality shall not affect the validity or constitutionality of the remaining portions of this ordinance, and the Board of Supervisors hereby declares that it would have passed this ordinance irrespective of such validity or unconstitutionality.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3255.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1141">Ord. 1141, 11/15/55</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.52.200</num>
      <heading>Possession and sale of firearms by county law enforcement officials.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(A)</num>
        <text>All firearms issued to county law enforcement officials shall be accompanied by a safety trigger lock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(B)</num>
        <text>No county law enforcement official shall sell, trade, give or otherwise transfer any firearm owned or possessed by the County of San Mateo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(C)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding subdivision (B) above, the County may sell any firearm owned or possessed by the County to another law enforcement agency, provided that the Sheriff has determined the firearm to be surplus property and the sale is otherwise permissible under applicable state and federal law.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(D)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding subdivision (B) above, the County may sell to any active Deputy, Sergeant, Lieutenant, Captain, Assistant Sheriff, Undersheriff, and Sheriff their County owned or possessed (department issued service firearm), provided that the Sheriff has determined the firearm to be surplus property and the firearm purchaser signs an agreement not to subsequently transfer the firearm except to the County.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3929">Ord. 3929, 11/16/99</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04734" path="§1">Ord. No. 04734, § 1, 3-31-2015</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.53</num>
    <heading>FIREARMS ON COUNTY PROPERTY</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.53.010</num>
      <heading>Possession of firearms on County property prohibited.</heading>
      <text>Every person who brings onto or possesses on County property a firearm, loaded or unloaded, or ammunition for a firearm is guilty of a misdemeanor.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4146">Ord. 4146, 12/17/02</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.53.020</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For purposes of <cite path="3.53">this chapter</cite>, the following definitions shall apply:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>County Property. As used in this section, the term County property means real property, including any buildings thereon, owned or leased by the County of San Mateo (hereinafter "County"), and in the County's possession, or in the possession of a public or private entity under contract with the County to perform a public purpose, including but not limited to real property owned or leased by the County in the unincorporated and incorporated portions of the County, and the San Mateo County Expo Center in the City of San Mateo, but does not include any "local public building" as defined in Penal Code Section 171b(c), where the State regulated possession of firearms pursuant to Penal Code Section 171.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Firearm. "Firearm" is any gun, pistol, revolver, rifle or any device, designed or modified to be used as a weapon, from which is expelled through a barrel a projectile by the force of an explosion or other form of combustion. "Firearm" does not include imitation firearms or BB guns and air rifles as defined in Government Code Section 53071.5.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Ammunition. "Ammunition" is any ammunition as defined in Penal Code Section 12316(b)(2).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4146">Ord. 4146, 12/17/02</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.53.030</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text>This section does not apply to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A peace officer as defined in <cite path="3">Title 3</cite>, Part 2, Chapter 4.5 of the California Penal Code (sections 830 et seq.);</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A guard or messenger of a financial institution, a guard of a contract carrier operating an armored vehicle, a licensed private investigator, patrol operator, or alarm company operator, or uniformed security guard as these occupations are defined in Penal Code section 12031(d) and who holds a valid certificate issued by the Department of Consumer Affairs under Penal Code section 12033, while actually employed and engaged in protecting and preserving property or life within the scope of his or her employment;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A person holding a valid license to carry a firearm issued pursuant to Penal Code section 12050;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>An authorized participant in a motion picture, television, video, dance, or theatrical production or event, when the participant lawfully uses the firearm as part of that production or event, provided that when such firearm is not in the actual possession of the authorized participant, it is secured to prevent unauthorized use;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>A person lawfully transporting firearms or ammunition in a motor vehicle on County roads;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>A person lawfully using the target range operated by the San Mateo County Sheriff;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>A federal criminal investigator or law enforcement officer; or</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>A member of the military forces of the State of California or of the United States.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4146">Ord. 4146, 12/17/02</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.54</num>
    <heading>SAFE STORAGE OF FIREARMS IN A RESIDENCE</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.54.010</num>
      <heading>Application of Chapter.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="3.54">this chapter</cite> shall apply within the unincorporated area of San Mateo County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04809" path="§2">Ord. No. 04809, § 2, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.54.020</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>For the purpose of <cite path="3.54">this chapter</cite>, "Firearm" means a firearm as defined in California Penal Code, Section 16520.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Locked Container" means a Locked Container, as defined in California Penal Code, Section 16850, listed on the California Department of Justice Bureau of Firearms roster of approved firearm safety devices. For purposes of <cite path="3.54">this chapter</cite>, a Locked Container does not include a bag or other container made of fabric or other penetrable material, such as a regular purse, backpack, or gym bag.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Residence" means any structure intended or used for human habitation, including but not limited to houses, condominiums, rooms, accessory dwelling units, motels, hotels, SRO's, time shares, recreational vehicles, and other vehicles where human habitation occurs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Trigger lock" means a trigger lock that is listed on the California Department of Justice's roster of approved firearms safety devices and that is identified as appropriate for that firearm by reference to either the manufacturer and model of the firearm or to the physical characteristics of the firearm that match those listed on the roster for use with the device under Penal Code section 23635.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04809" path="§2">Ord. No. 04809, § 2, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.54.030</num>
      <heading>Safe storage of firearms in a residence required.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except when carried on the person, no person shall keep a Firearm in any Residence unless the Firearm is stored in a Locked Container or is disabled with a Trigger Lock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>To encourage reporting of lost or stolen Firearms, a person who complies with California Penal Code section 25250 by reporting the loss or theft of a Firearm they own or possess to a local law enforcement agency within five days from the time they knew or reasonably should have known the Firearm had been lost or stolen shall not be prosecuted for violation of subsection (a).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04809" path="§2">Ord. No. 04809, § 2, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.54.040</num>
      <heading>Penalty.</heading>
      <text>A violation of this section shall be subject to enforcement through criminal prosecution and/or civil penalties, as provided herein.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Violation a Misdemeanor. A person who violates <cite path="3.54">this chapter</cite> shall be guilty of a misdemeanor punishable by imprisonment in the county jail not exceeding six (6) months or by fine not exceeding one thousand dollars ($1,000.00), or by both.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Civil Penalties. The County may assess civil penalties pursuant to San Mateo County Municipal Code <cite path="1.40">Chapter 1.40</cite> (Administrative Remedies) in the amounts provided in <cite path="1.40.070">Section 1.40.070</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Each violation shall be deemed a distinct and separate offense.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04809" path="§2">Ord. No. 04809, § 2, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.54.050</num>
      <heading>Effective Date.</heading>
      <text>This Ordinance shall be in effect thirty (30) days after adoption.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04809" path="§2">Ord. No. 04809, § 2, 2-26-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.56</num>
    <heading>HUNTING ON PRIVATE PROPERTY</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.56.010</num>
      <heading>Hunting on private property prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to hunt, shoot, or trespass, while in the possession of firearms, on any private property without first having procured and without having in his or her possession the written consent of the owner or owners or lessee or lessees of such private property.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3260</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 159">Ord. 159, 12/18/1899</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 342">Ord. 342, 11/09/25</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.56.020</num>
      <heading>Hunting on county roads or public roads.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to hunt, shoot, pursue, or kill any game or other birds on any County road or public highway of San Mateo County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3261</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 159">Ord. 159, 12/18/1899</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.56.030</num>
      <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
      <text>It shall be the duty of the sheriff, constables, and all peace officers to enforce <cite path="3.56">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3262</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 342">Ord. 342, 11/09/25</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.60</num>
    <heading>EXPLOSIVES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.010</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.60">this chapter</cite>, the following terms shall have the meanings stated herein:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Board" means the Board of Supervisors of the County of San Mateo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Explosive" means any substance, or combination of substances, the primary or common purpose of which is detonation or rapid combustion and which is capable of a relatively instantaneous or rapid release of gas and heat, or any substance, the primary purpose of which, when combined with others, is to form a substance capable of a relatively instantaneous or rapid release of gas and heat. The term "explosive" includes, but is not necessarily limited to, those substances and things defined as "explosives" in section 12000 of the Health and Safety Code of the State of California.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3265</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.020</num>
      <heading>Blasting.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person, without first obtaining a license from the Sheriff of the County of San Mateo as herein provided, to do any blasting within the unincorporated area of the County of San Mateo or to explode, or cause to be exploded, any explosive.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3266</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.030</num>
      <heading>Blasting license.</heading>
      <text>Any person desiring to use explosives within the unincorporated area of the County of San Mateo for the purpose of blasting shall make written application to the Sheriff for a license. Said application shall set forth the name, age and address of the applicant and a statement of his or her previous experience with, and qualifications safely to handle and use, explosives. If the Sheriff is satisfied that a license therefor should be issued to the applicant, the Sheriff may issue such a license after the applicant has deposited with the County Clerk an indemnity bond in an amount deemed sufficient for its purpose by the Sheriff, but in no case in an amount less than one thousand dollars ($1,000), in favor of the County of San Mateo and inuring to the benefit of that County and all persons who may suffer damage to person or property as a result of the blasting to be done by the applicant. Said indemnity bond shall be conditioned to pay for all loss or damage to person or property caused or resulting from blasting operations by the applicant. Said bond shall be approved by the County Counsel before being filed with the County Clerk. After a recovery had upon said bond, the licensee shall immediately file a new bond in the same form, and if the licensee does not do so, said license shall immediately terminate. In the event that the Sheriff refuses to issue a license to an applicant, the applicant may appeal to the Board for a review of the Sheriff's decision.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3267</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3214">Ord. 3214, 4/24/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.040</num>
      <heading>Term of license.</heading>
      <text>The license provided for in <cite path="3.60.030">section 3.60.030</cite> shall remain in force for a period of one year from the date upon which it was issued by the Sheriff.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3268</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.050</num>
      <heading>License fee.</heading>
      <text>Before any license provided for in <cite path="3.60.030">section 3.60.030</cite> shall become effective, the licensee named therein shall pay to the Sheriff a fee of ten ($10) dollars.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3269</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.060</num>
      <heading>Blasting operations.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person to explode, or cause to explode, any blast without first covering the same in such a manner as to prevent fragments of rock, gravel, earth, trees or other substances and material from being thrown against or upon lots or buildings, or upon any public roadway.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3270</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.60.070</num>
      <heading>Temporary suspension of license.</heading>
      <text>When, in the opinion of the Sheriff, the use of any license provided for in <cite path="3.60.030">section 3.60.030</cite> may endanger the public health, welfare or safety, the Sheriff may suspend such a license for any period of time less than one (1) year.</text>
      <text>As soon as it can practicably be done, and before the actual date of such suspension if circumstances permit, notice in writing of such suspension shall be given by the Sheriff to the licensee. Notice may be given by personal delivery to the licensee or by depositing in the United States mail, with postage prepaid, such notice in an envelope addressed to the licensee at the licensee's address shown on the application for the license.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3271</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 704">Ord. 704, 12/17/46</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2344">Ord. 2344, 01/06/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.61</num>
    <heading>USE, POSSESSION, TRANSFER, OFFER FOR SALE AND SALE OF FLAMETHROWERS PROHIBITED</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.010</num>
      <heading>Application of Chapter.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite> shall apply within the unincorporated area of San Mateo County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.020</num>
      <heading>Flamethrower Defined.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite>, "flamethrower" means any nonstationary and transportable device designed or intended to emit, or capable of emitting or propelling, fire or a burning stream of combustible or flammable liquid a distance of twenty-two (22) inches or greater.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.030</num>
      <heading>Possession and Use of Flamethrowers Prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person shall possess or use any flamethrower.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.040</num>
      <heading>Sale, Transfer, or Distribution of Flamethrowers Prohibited.</heading>
      <text>The sale, offer or display for sale, trade, transfer, or other distribution by any person or retailer of flamethrowers is prohibited and no person or retailer shall sell, offer or display for sale, trade, transfer, or distribute, any flamethrower.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.050</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text><cite path="3.61">This chapter</cite> shall not apply to the possession, transportation, storage, or use of a flamethrower by a person if all of the following apply:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>The person is regularly employed by, or a paid officer, employee, or member of, a fire department, fire protection district, or firefighting agency of the federal government, the state, a city, a county, a city and county, district, public or municipal corporation, or other political subdivision of the state of California.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The person is on duty and acting within the course and scope of his or her employment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The flamethrower is used by the fire department, fire protection district, or firefighting agency described in subdivision (a) in the course of fire suppression or fire suppression training.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text><cite path="3.61">This chapter</cite> shall not apply to prohibit the storage on private property only of a flamethrower by a person who is an active permitholder pursuant to Division 11, Part 3, § 12750, et, seq. of the California Health and Safety Code, or successor statute.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.060</num>
      <heading>Violation of this chapter is a Public Nuisance.</heading>
      <text>Violation of <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite> is a public nuisance subject to any and all applicable civil, administrative and criminal remedies and penalties according to the provisions and procedures contained in this ordinance code and state law including, but not limited to, an abatement action for seizure and destruction of the flamethrower.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.070</num>
      <heading>Enforcement.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The San Mateo County Sheriff or designee, or any code enforcement officer appointed by the County, may enforce <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A violation of <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite> is an infraction, punishable by:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>A fine not exceeding one hundred dollars ($100.00) for a first violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>A fine not exceeding two hundred dollars ($200.00) for the second violation within one year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>A fine not exceeding five hundred dollars ($500.00) for each additional violation within one year.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>This section shall not be interpreted to limit the applicable civil or administrative remedies available under law.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.080</num>
      <heading>No Conflict with Federal or State Law.</heading>
      <text>Nothing in <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite> shall be interpreted or applied so as to create any requirement, power, or duty that is preempted by federal or state law.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.61.090</num>
      <heading>Severability.</heading>
      <text>If any provision, section, subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, or word of this <cite path="3.61">Chapter 3.61</cite>, or any application thereof to any person or circumstance, is held to be invalid or unconstitutional by a court of competent jurisdiction, such decision shall not affect the validity of the remaining portions or applications of the chapter. The Board of Supervisors hereby declares that it would have passed <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite>, and each provision, section, subsection, sentence, clause, phrase, and word not declared invalid or unconstitutional without regard to whether any portion of <cite path="3.61">this chapter</cite> or application thereof would be subsequently declared invalid or unconstitutional.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04804" path="§1">Ord. No. 04804, § 1, 9-25-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.64</num>
    <heading>LOGGING PRACTICES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.64.010</num>
      <heading>Prohibitions.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person, firm or corporation, whether as principal, servant, agent or employee to do any of the following acts:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Engage in or carry on, or maintain or conduct, or cause to be engaged in or carried on, maintained or conducted, any operations to log, process, or move timber, trees or brush from or on lands contiguous to or containing streams, creek beds, or ditches without first removing logs, slash, and debris from in or within sixty (60) feet of said streams, creek beds, or ditches on the land within which said operations are to be carried on;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Deposit or cause to be deposited any logs, slash and debris in or within sixty (60) feet of streams, creek beds, or ditches contiguous to or within lands on which there is engaged or carried on, maintained or conducted or caused to be engaged in, carried on, maintained or conducted any operations to log, process or move timber, tree, or brush;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any other act or acts which may cause or does cause change in the course of streams or erosion of their banks or undermining at culverts, bridges, abutments, and other structures or the obstruction of flow of water through entrances to such culverts, under bridges or past structures, except as the construction or reconstruction of roads, bridges, culverts, and other authorized projects may require changes in water courses.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3380</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 991">Ord. 991, 08/05/52</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.68</num>
    <heading>COUNTY PARK AND RECREATION AREA RULES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.010</num>
      <heading>Violations, a misdemeanor.</heading>
      <text>Any person violating any of the provisions or failing to comply with any of the mandatory requirements of <cite path="3.68">this chapter</cite> shall be guilty of a misdemeanor, unless otherwise specified.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3385</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04805" path="§2">Ord. No. 04805, § 2, 11-6-2018</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.020</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this ordinance shall not apply to employees of the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department, or the San Francisco Water Department, or other public officials acting within the scope of their authorized duties. However, Department employees, public officials and concessionaires and their employees shall abide by the laws of the State of California and all applicable County and/or municipal ordinances.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3385.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04805" path="§2">Ord. No. 04805, § 2, 11-6-2018</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.030</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Commission" shall mean the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Commission.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"County Park" shall mean any park, recreation area, reserve or preserve, historical site or any other facility operated, owned, or managed by the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Department" shall mean the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Director" shall mean the Director of the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"General Manager and Chief Engineer" shall mean the General Manager and Chief Engineer of the San Francisco Water Department of the City and County of San Francisco.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge" means that area defined in the State of California Fish and Game Code, division 7 REFUGES, chapter 2, article 1, section 10771 and under the jurisdiction of the San Francisco Water Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"Hiking and Riding Trail" shall mean all trails which have been dedicated to the County or other public agency for hiking or horseback riding purposes, or both, or any trail which is open to the general public for such purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>"Motor Vehicle" shall mean any automobile, truck, bus, van, motorcycle, off-road vehicle, four-wheel drive vehicle, dirt bike, motor-driven vehicle, or any vehicle which is self-propelled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>"Person" as used in <cite path="3.68">this chapter</cite> shall be construed to mean and shall include natural persons, firms, co-partnerships, corporations, clubs and all associations or combinations of persons whatsoever, whether acting by themselves or by a servant, agent or employee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>"Recreation Area" as used in <cite path="3.68">this chapter</cite> shall be construed to mean and shall include all land, facilities and other property for public recreation owned and/or operated by the County of San Mateo, or the San Francisco Water Department, including parks, playgrounds, camping areas, swimming pools, golf courses, picnic grounds, athletic fields, beaches, parkways, public squares, hiking and bicycling paths, horse trails, roadside viewing areas, rest stops, historical monuments, and all grounds surrounding public buildings, all planting and areas for planting along roads, streets and highways, and all other recreation areas, including all buildings, structures, improvements, monuments, apparatus and equipment existing in or that may be erected in any of such areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>"Sound Amplifying Equipment" shall mean any machine or device for the amplification of the human voice, music, or any other sound, but shall not include standard automobile radios or automobile tape decks when used and heard only by the occupants of the vehicle in which the automobile radio or tape deck is installed, nor radio receiving sets, non-electrical musical instruments, or television sets. "Sound Amplifying Equipment" as used in <cite path="3.68">this chapter</cite>, shall not include warning devices or sound amplification equipment on Parks and Recreation Department, or San Francisco Water Department vehicles, or other authorized emergency vehicles, or horns, or other warning devices on any vehicle used only for traffic safety purposes.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>"Vessel" shall be used to describe any water craft, board or similar equipment capable of being used as transportation in or on water.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>"Beach" shall mean the shore of any body of water within any County Park and Recreation Area or the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3385.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04805" path="§2">Ord. No. 04805, § 2, 11-6-2018</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.040</num>
      <heading>Permits and fees—Violation as infraction.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall enter, occupy or use a County park or Recreation Area, or any area or facility therein, for which a user fee, deposit or permit is required without first obtaining any applicable permit and paying any applicable fees or deposits in the manner provided by <cite path="3.68">this chapter</cite>. Any person obtaining a permit to enter or use a County park or Recreation Area shall display such permit in the manner provided by such permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person shall enter a self-registration fee payment area without first (1) depositing the applicable fees; and (2) completing and prominently displaying the permit, so that the permit number is clearly legible from the outside of the vehicle entering the park or recreation area, according to all applicable guidelines either posted at the fee collection vault or printed on the permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A violation of this section shall be an infraction punishable by (1) a fine not exceeding one hundred dollars ($100.00) for a first violation; (2) a fine not exceeding two hundred dollars ($200.00) for a second violation of this section within one year; and (3) a fine not exceeding five hundred dollars ($500.00) for each additional violation of this section within one year.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3385.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04805" path="§2">Ord. No. 04805, § 2, 11-6-2018</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3651">Ord. 3651, 5/16/95</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.050</num>
      <heading>Method of payment of fees.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Except as otherwise provided by this code, all fees and deposits established by the Parks and Recreation Commission for entry or use of County park and recreation areas or for designated privileges, services or materials, shall be paid to the Director or his or her designee in the manner determined by the Director. All fees collected shall be deposited in the Treasury of the County of San Mateo and shall be credited to the appropriate fund.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The Director may, subject to approval by the Parks and Recreation Commission, designate any recreation area or county park a "self-registration fee payment area." Payment of applicable fees for entry or use of a self-registration fee payment area shall be by deposit into a fee collection vault located at the entrance to such park or recreation area. The Director may establish, subject to approval by the Parks and Recreation Commission, policies and procedures for collection of such fees including the hours and dates of collection. Pursuant to guidelines approved by the Parks and Recreation Commission, the Director may waive payment and suspend collection of applicable fees at any self-registration fee payment area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>All fee deposit envelopes, permits and receipts shall remain the property of the County of San Mateo and shall be subject to inspection by, and surrendered upon demand to, the Director, or any County Park Ranger or law enforcement officer. Fees deposited in any fee collection vault, including any overpayment, are non-refundable. If the fee deposited is insufficient to pay in full the applicable fee, the remaining balance shall be due and payable to the Director or County Park Ranger upon demand.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3385.4</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3651">Ord. 3651, 5/16/95</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.060</num>
      <heading>Camping regulations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Permits. A permit must be obtained from the County Parks and Recreation Commission or its authorized staff before camping in any recreation area or in any County Park, and camping is not permitted outside the campsite or sites designated on said permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Camping by Minors. Persons under the age of 18 are not permitted to camp overnight in any recreation area or in any County Park unless accompanied by an adult.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3386</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 976">Ord. 976, 01/15/52</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2307">Ord. 2307, 05/06/75</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.070</num>
      <heading>Fires.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall light, build, use or maintain a fire within any Recreation area or any County Park, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, except in places specifically provided therefor, and said places shall not be used until user has removed all dead wood, moss, dry leaves or other combustible material which may have gathered around said place so that there is no possible danger of any fire spreading.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person responsible for an authorized fire in any Recreation area or in any County Park, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, shall leave said fire unattended. When the user has finished with the fire, it shall be completely extinguished.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3386.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1639">Ord. 1639, 02/25/64</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.080</num>
      <heading>General protective regulations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Vegetative. No person shall willfully or negligently pick, dig up, cut, mutilate, destroy, injure, disturb, move, molest, burn, carry away, collect or gather any tree or plant or portion thereof, including but not limited to leaf mold, flowers, foliage, berries, fruit, grass, turf, humus, shrubs, cones, ferns, mushrooms and dead wood in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, or on any hiking and riding trail, nor shall any person willfully or negligently allow any dog to do so. Nothing in this section shall prevent the taking of any tree or plant or portion thereof, including but not limited to leaf mold, flowers, foliage, berries, fruit, grass, turf, humus, shrubs, cones, ferns, mushrooms and dead wood in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, any hiking and riding trail by public officials pursuant to their official duties or by scientific permit from the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department, or San Francisco Water Department, for the areas under their respective jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Vandalism (Property). No person shall disturb, destroy, remove, deface or injure any property of the County of San Mateo or the City and County of San Francisco which is located in any Recreation area or in any County Park or hiking and riding trail, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge. No person shall cut, carve, paint, mark, paste, or fasten on any tree, fence, wall, building, monument or other property in any County Park or Recreation area, or hiking and riding trail, or other property in any County Park or Recreation area, or hiking and riding trail, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, any advertisement, sign or inscription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Littering. No person shall place or throw bottles, broken glass, crockery, ashes, waste paper, cans, dog waste (bagged or unbagged), or any decaying or putrid matter or other rubbish in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, except in a receptacle designated for that purpose, and no person shall import or deposit any rubbish into or in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, or hiking and riding trail. No person shall transport or dump any rock, rubble, dirt, sand, fill or other similar material into or in any County Park or Recreation area without the permission of the Director, or the General Manager and Chief Engineer, or their representatives for the areas under their respective jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Reserves and Preserves. All geological and archeological features, plants and animals (dead or alive) are protected and taking is prohibited except the taking of such plants and animals as are permitted by regulations specific to the area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Watershed Protection. No person shall allow any dog to contaminate in any way whatsoever any watershed or water supply in any Recreation area or in any County Park, or in the Watershed, or water supplies of any water purveyor holding a water purveyor's permit issued by the California Department of Health Services pursuant to Public Health Code, Chapter 7, Section 4011.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Water Quality Protection. No person shall wash clothing or cooking utensils, bathe in, or in any other manner pollute the waters of any Recreation Area or any County Park, nor shall any person leave bagged or unbagged feces or in any other manner pollute the waters of any Recreation Area or any County Park, or in the Watershed, or water supplies of any water purveyor holding a water purveyor's permit issued by the California Department of Health Services pursuant to Public Health Code, Chapter 7, Section 4011.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Geological Features Protection. No person shall destroy, disturb, mutilate or remove earth, sand, gravel, oil, minerals, rocks, or features of caves, or lay, or set off any explosive material or cause to be done or assist in doing any of said things in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, or hiking and riding trail without the specific permission of the Director or the General Manager and Chief Engineer, or their representative, for the areas under their respective jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Protection of Historical Features. No person shall remove, injure, disfigure, deface or destroy any object of paleontological, archaeological, or historical interest or value in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, or hiking and riding trail nor shall any person engage in any excavation for said objects without first receiving written permission from the Director, or the General Manager and Chief Engineer, or their representatives, for the areas under their respective jurisdictions.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Domestic Animals. Except as expressly permitted pursuant to <cite path="3.68.180">Section 3.68.180</cite>, no dogs, cats, fowl or other domesticated animals shall be permitted to enter or go at large in any County Park or Recreation area, either with or without a keeper. No person shall release any captured wild animal within any County Park or Recreation area except authorized public officials pursuant to their duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Abandoned Animals. No person shall abandon a dog, cat, fowl or other animal within any County Park or Recreation area, or in the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Feeding Domesticated Animals. No person shall feed any abandoned domesticated animal in any County Park or Recreation area, or in the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>Grazing. The running at large, herding or grazing of livestock of any kind in any County Park or Recreation area, or driving of livestock over same, is prohibited unless a lease of the land has been granted for that purpose. Livestock found in any County Park or Recreation area may be impounded and held until claimed by the owner and payment made for any damages caused and for any expenses incurred by the County in impounding and holding such livestock.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>Horses Off Trails or Out of Designated Areas. No person shall ride, drive, lead, or keep a saddle horse, pony, mule or other such animal in any County Park or Recreation area except on such roads, trails or areas so designated and posted by the Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>Wildlife. All County Parks and Recreation Areas and the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge are sanctuaries for wildlife. No person shall feed, approach, disturb, frighten, hunt, trap, capture, wound, kill, chase, pursue, or disturb the natural habitat of, any wild bird, mammal, reptile, fish, amphibian or invertebrate within a County Park or Recreation Area or within any San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge area located within the County, nor shall any person allow any dog to do so. This prohibition shall not apply to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Action taken by public officials or their employees or agents, within the scope of their authorized duties, to protect the public health and safety.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The taking of fish as permitted by State Fish and Game Regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The capturing and/or taking of park wildlife for scientific research purposes when done with written permission from the Director of the San Mateo County Division of Parks and Recreation or, in the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, from the San Francisco Water Department.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <text>Firearms and Dangerous Weapons. Except as provided in subsection (p) and subsection (q), no person shall have in his possession within any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, and no person shall fire or discharge, or cause to be fired or discharged, across, in, or into any portion of any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, any gun or firearm, spear, bow and arrow, cross bow, slingshot, air or gas weapon or any other dangerous weapon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(p)</num>
        <text>Shooting Ranges. The discharge or firing of firearms is permitted in areas designated by the Parks and Recreation Commission, or San Francisco Water Department, specifically for the purposes of rifle and/or pistol and/or shotgun shooting, and the transportation of such firearms through the County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, in which said area(s) is/are located is permitted providing said firearms are unloaded. "Unloaded" shall mean that there is no ammunition in either the chamber or magazine of the gun.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(q)</num>
        <text>Archery Ranges. The use of a bow and arrow, but not a crossbow, is permitted in areas designated by the Parks and Recreation Commission specifically for the purpose of archery, but all bows must be unstrung during transportation to and from such designated areas.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(r)</num>
        <text>Loitering After Closing Time. It shall be unlawful for any person to remain in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, or in any facility within any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, after the posted closing time, unless said person has lawful business therein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(s)</num>
        <text>Gambling. Gambling in any form, or the operation of gambling devices for merchandise or otherwise in any County Park or Recreation area is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(t)</num>
        <text>Alcoholic Beverages. No person shall possess or consume alcoholic beverages, other than beer or wine, in any form within any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge. Alcoholic beverages as described herein are permitted at Coyote Point County Park only in designated areas and during designated times. No person shall possess or consume any alcoholic beverages in any form at the Coyote Point Rifle and Pistol Range, or within twenty-five (25) feet of the San Francisco Watershed vehicle parking lots or areas. This section shall not prohibit the dispensing of all types of alcoholic beverages by a licensee under the laws of the State of California, under a food and bar concession from the County or the consumption of such beverages on the premises of such concessionaire, or the consumption of alcoholic beverages by persons holding a written occupancy permit issued by the Parks Director, or his or her representative, for areas under his or her jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(u)</num>
        <text>Private Operations. It shall be unlawful for any person to engage in the business of soliciting, selling or peddling of any liquids or edibles for human consumption or to distribute circulars or to hawk, peddle or vend any goods, wares or merchandise of any kind, except upon specific concession or permit secured from the Commission, or the General Manager and Chief Engineer, or his representative, for areas under his jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(v)</num>
        <text>Authorized Operations. All persons, firms, or corporations holding concessions shall keep the grounds used by them properly policed and shall maintain the premises in a sanitary condition to the satisfaction of the Director or General Manager and Chief Engineer for areas under their respective jurisdictions. No operator of any concession shall retain in his employment any person whose presence is deemed by the District or General Manager and Chief Engineer for their respective jurisdictions not to be conducive to good order and management.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(w)</num>
        <text>Commercial Filming. No person shall operate a still, motion picture, video or other camera for commercial purposes in any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, except pursuant to a written permit from the Director or the General Manager and Chief Engineer, or their representative, for the areas under their respective jurisdictions authorizing such activity. This section shall not apply to the commercial operation of cameras as part of the bonafide reporting of news.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(x)</num>
        <text>Closed Areas. No person shall enter any road, trail or area that is posted as closed or restricted without permission from the County Parks and Recreation Director.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3387</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04805" path="§2">Ord. No. 04805, § 2, 11-6-2018</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 976">Ord. 976, 01/15/52</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1287">Ord. 1287, 05/06/58</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3796">Ord. 3796, 11/4/97</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3863">Ord. 3863, 12/1/98</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.090</num>
      <heading>Motor vehicles.</heading>
      <text>No person shall operate any motor vehicle except upon established paved roads or other established paved areas specifically designated and maintained for normal ingress, egress, and parking. This section shall not apply to any emergency or County vehicle, physically handicapped persons operating wheelchairs or similar devices, or to any person acting in compliance with the directions of a Park Ranger or Peace Officer.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3388</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 976">Ord. 976, 01/15/52</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.100</num>
      <heading>Parking.</heading>
      <text>No person shall park any motor vehicle as defined in <cite path="3.68">this chapter</cite> within a County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, except upon areas designated for such use. No person shall park a motor vehicle, except an authorized emergency vehicle or when in compliance with the directions of a Peace Officer or Park Ranger in any of the following places: In areas where prohibited by "NO PARKING" signs. On any fire trail, road or access. On any equestrian or hiking trail. Blocking or obstructing any gate, entrance or exit. On any lawn or grassy area. In any picnic area. On any beach. In such a manner as to take up more than one "Marked" space in any authorized parking area. In any area where such vehicle blocks or obstructs the free flow of traffic. Within 15 feet of a fire hydrant. Adjacent to any curb painted red. In any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, after closing time except pursuant to a valid permit.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3388.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.110</num>
      <heading>Motor vehicle speed limits.</heading>
      <text>No person shall drive a motor vehicle within any County Park or Recreation area, or the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, at a speed greater than is reasonable or prudent, having due regard for traffic and the surface and width of the road, and in no event at a speed which endangers the safety of person, property, or wildlife, provided, however, that in no event shall a motor vehicle be driven at a speed greater than the posted speed limit for that area as designated by the Parks and Recreation Commission.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3388.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.120</num>
      <heading>Operation of bicycles; violation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall operate a bicycle in any County Park or Recreation Area, including but not limited to Sawyer Camp Trail or San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, other than on a path designated and signed for that purpose or on a paved vehicular road meant for motor vehicles. All bicyclists shall ride in single file, except to pass. No bicyclist shall exceed a safe speed.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No bicyclist on Sawyer Camp Trail shall exceed a speed of 5 miles per hour within one-eighth-mile from each end of Sawyer Camp Trail. No bicyclist on Sawyer Camp Trail shall exceed a speed of 15 miles per hour on the rest of Sawyer Camp Trail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>A violation of the provisions of this section shall be an infraction. Any person to whom a citation is issued for a violation of this section shall be subject to a fine of Fifty Dollars ($50) for a first violation within a period of one year, One Hundred Dollars ($100) for a second violation within a period of one year, and Three Hundred Dollars ($300) for each additional violation within a period of one year.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3388.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3272">Ord. 3272, 10/23/90</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3351">Ord. 3351, 12/10/91</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3471">Ord. 3471, 02/02/93</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.130</num>
      <heading>Noise.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Declaration of Noise Policy. It is hereby declared to be the policy of the Parks and Recreation Commission, and the San Francisco Water Department, to prohibit unnecessary, excessive, and annoying noises in all County Parks, and the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge. At certain levels, noises are detrimental to the health and welfare of persons using County Parks or Recreation areas, and it is in the public interest to proscribe such noises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Sound Amplifying Equipment. It shall be unlawful for any person to operate any sound amplifying equipment as defined in <cite path="3.68.030">section 3.68.030</cite> in any County Park or Recreation area, or the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge. This section shall not apply to a person operating sound amplifying equipment under a permit granted by the Parks and Recreation Department, or the San Francisco Water Department, as provided in <cite path="3.68.140">section 3.68.140</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Peace and Quiet. It shall be unlawful for any person within any County Park or the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge to use or operate any radio receiving set, musical instrument, machine or device for producing or reproducing sound or any device which produces noise in such a manner as to disturb the reasonable peace, quiet and comfort of persons using any County Park or Recreation area or the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Noise, Absolute Prohibition. No person shall use or operate any of the devices mentioned in subsection (c) within the campgrounds of any County Park or Recreation area and the San Francisco Water Department area(s) between the hours of 10:00 P.M. and 8:00 A.M.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3389</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 976">Ord. 976, 01/15/52</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1287">Ord. 1287, 05/06/58</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.140</num>
      <heading>Unlawful assembly.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person or group to conduct a group meeting, rally, or similar gathering in any County Park or Recreation area without first obtaining a permit from the Parks and Recreation Department for the use of the area or facility involved. The division shall grant such permit unless it finds that the time and/or place and/or size of the meeting, rally, or similar gathering may unreasonably interfere with the normal use or operation of the area or facility requested. Said permit shall be obtained at least ten days prior to such activity.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3390</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 976">Ord. 976, 01/15/52</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.150</num>
      <heading>Dangerous activities.</heading>
      <text>Except in areas specifically designated and set aside from time to time by the Parks and Recreation Commission, or the San Francisco Water Department for such activities, no person shall engage in any of the following activities within any County Park or Recreation area, or on the San Francisco Fish and Game Refuge, and in no case shall any person engage in any activity or operate any device recklessly or negligently so as to endanger the life, limb or property of any person:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Use or possess fireworks of any kind.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Drive, chip, or in any other manner play or practice golf, or hit golf balls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Operate self-propelled model airplanes, boats, automobiles, or other model craft of any kind or description.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Throw, release, or discharge missiles, rockets, or similar projectiles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Hang-glide or parachute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Operate any gas or hot air balloon (other than a toy balloon).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3391</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 415">Ord. 415, 06/25/34</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2307">Ord. 2307, 05/06/75</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2807">Ord. 2807, 10/26/82</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.160</num>
      <heading>Hiking and riding trails.</heading>
      <text>The following regulations shall apply to any and all persons using hiking and riding trails in the County of San Mateo.</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No loaded firearm shall be carried on any hiking and riding trail, except by Peace Officers, nor shall any person discharge across, in or into any portion of a hiking and riding trail any firearm or other device capable of injuring or killing any person, animal or damaging or destroying any public or private property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person shall disturb, destroy, remove, deface or injure any property on a hiking and riding trail. No person shall cut, carve, paint, mark, paste or fasten on any tree, fence, wall, building, monument or other property along or on such trail any bill, advertisement or inscription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>No person shall use threatening, abusive, boisterous, insulting or indecent language or make indecent gestures on a hiking or riding trail; nor shall any person conduct or participate in a disorderly assemblage thereon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>No person shall operate a vehicle on a hiking and riding trail other than a vehicle used for emergency or maintenance purposes or such other vehicle as may be especially designated by the Director of Parks and Recreation Department, unless the trail traverses a common right-of-way.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>No person shall molest livestock encountered on or adjacent to a hiking and riding trail.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>No person shall ride any saddle animal on a hiking and riding trail in a manner that might endanger life or limb of any person or animal, and no person shall allow his/her saddle or pack animal to stand unattended or insecurely tied.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>All persons using a hiking and riding trail shall respect the rights of property owners along the trail and shall not trespass on their property or invade their privacy in any way.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Every person using a hiking and riding trail shall promptly report any uncontrolled fire in sight of the trail to the nearest Peace Officer, Park Ranger or fire station.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>All persons opening a closed gate on or near a hiking and riding trail shall securely close same after passing through it.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>No campfire shall be built on or adjacent to a hiking and riding trail except in areas specifically provided and marked for that purpose.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Smoking on hiking and riding trails is prohibited.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3392</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2394">Ord. 2394, 09/21/76</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.170</num>
      <heading>Beaches and swimming areas.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No motor or wind-powered vessel shall be permitted in any designated swimming area in any San Mateo County Park or Recreation area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No vessel with motor or capable of carrying a motor may be launched in any San Mateo County Park or Recreation area except in designated launching areas.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3393</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3252">Ord. 3252, 07/31/90</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.68.180</num>
      <heading>Dogs.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No dogs shall be permitted in any San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area, unless such area is specifically designated and signed to allow dogs. This subsection shall not apply to (i) service dogs under physical control, specifically trained to assist persons with disabilities in accordance with the American's with Disabilities Act or (ii) a "police dog" under the control of a peace officer.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>In any San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area where dogs are allowed, no person shall have more than three dogs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>No person shall cause or allow any dog under his or her ownership, possession, or control to enter or remain in any San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area unless the dog is licensed as required by the County of San Mateo, is wearing around its neck a collar and valid license tag, and the owner or possessor of the dog complies with all other conditions of this <cite path="3.68.180">Section 3.68.180</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In any San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area where dogs are allowed, no person shall cause or allow any dog under his or her ownership, possession, or control to enter or remain in such area unless such person restrains such dog, at all times, with a leash not to exceed six (6) feet in length (sixteen (16) feet when unretracted) and insures that the leash and control by the person are sufficient to prevent endangering other persons or animals. Where dogs are permitted only on designated trails, any dog shall be restricted to the designated trails at all times and shall not be allowed to enter the natural habitat abutting the designated trails.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Any person bringing a dog into any San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area shall immediately remove any feces deposited by such dog. Dog feces must be placed in garbage cans or removed from the San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area. No person shall bring a dog into any San Mateo County Park or Recreation Area without carrying at all times a suitable container or other suitable instrument for the removal and disposal of dog feces.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>A violation of the provisions of this section shall be an infraction. Any person to whom a citation is issued for a violation of this section shall be subject to a base fine of:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Five Dollars ($5.00) for a first violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>Thirty Dollars ($30.00) for a second violation within a period of one year from the first violation; and</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>One Hundred Dollars ($100.00) for each additional violation within a period of one year from the first violation.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3387.5</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04805" path="§2">Ord. No. 04805, § 2, 11-6-2018</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3370">Ord. 3370, 02/11/92</annotation>
        <annotation type="History">to be in effect for one year</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04812" path="§2">Ord. No. 04812, § 2, 5-14-2019</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.69</num>
    <heading>TUNITAS CREEK BEACH</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.010</num>
      <heading>Violations, a misdemeanor.</heading>
      <text>Any violation of any of the provisions of this <cite path="3.69">chapter 3.69</cite>, or any failure to comply with any of the mandatory requirements of this <cite path="3.69">chapter 3.69</cite>, shall be a misdemeanor.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.020</num>
      <heading>Exceptions.</heading>
      <text>The provisions of this ordinance shall not apply to the following:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>the fee owners of the property described in <cite path="3.69.030|(c)">section 3.69.030(c)</cite>, their tenants, invitees and guests; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>employees of the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department or other public officials or San Mateo County concessionaires acting within the scope of their authorized duties or authorized concession activities. However, County employees, public officials and concessionaires and their employees shall abide by the laws of the State of California and all applicable County and/or municipal ordinances.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.030</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Words used in <cite path="3.69">this chapter</cite> shall have the meanings given them under <cite path="3.68.030">section 3.68.030</cite> of this Code, unless separately defined herein.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Beach" shall mean the shore of the Pacific Ocean within the Tunitas Creek Beach property.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Tunitas Creek Beach" shall mean all that area situated in the unincorporated territory of the County of San Mateo, State of California, that is part of the Rancho San Gregorio west of Highway 1 at Tunitas Creek Road, historically known as Tunitas Creek Beach, and more particularly described as follows: All that certain area of land lying westerly of State Highway Route No. 1, from a northerly point due west of Postmile 21.3 to a southerly point due west of Postmile 20.2, and all hiking and riding trails thereto, and all portions of the Tunitas Creek riparian corridor within the State of California right-of-way for Highway 1.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.040</num>
      <heading>Camping regulations.</heading>
      <text>No overnight camping shall be permitted at any time on Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.050</num>
      <heading>Fires.</heading>
      <text>No person shall light, build, use or maintain a fire at any time within Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.060</num>
      <heading>General protective regulations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Vegetative. No person shall willfully or negligently pick, dig up, cut, mutilate, destroy, injure, disturb, move, molest, burn, carry away, collect or gather any tree or plant or portion thereof, including but not limited to leaf mold, flowers, foliage, berries, fruit, grass, turf, humus, shrubs, cones, ferns, mushrooms and dead wood in Tunitas Creek Beach. Nothing in this section shall prevent the taking of any tree or plant or portion thereof, including but not limited to leaf mold, flowers, foliage, berries, fruit, grass, turf, humus, shrubs, cones, ferns, mushrooms and dead wood at Tunitas Creek Beach by scientific permit from the San Mateo County Parks and Recreation Department for the areas under its jurisdiction.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Vandalism (Property). No person shall disturb, destroy, remove, deface or injure any property at Tunitas Creek Beach. No person shall cut, carve, paint, mark, paste, or fasten on any tree, fence, wall, building, monument or other property at Tunitas Creek Beach, or hiking and riding trail thereto, any advertisement, sign or inscription.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Littering. No person shall place or throw bottles, broken glass, crockery, ashes, waste paper, cans or any decaying or putrid matter or other rubbish at Tunitas Creek Beach, and no person shall import or deposit any rubbish into or at Tunitas Creek Beach or any hiking and riding trail thereto.. No person shall transport or dump any rock, rubble, dirt, sand, fill or other similar material into or at Tunitas Creek Beach except pursuant to a permit issued by the County of San Mateo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Reserves and Preserves. All geological and archeological features, plants and animals (dead or alive) are protected and any taking is prohibited except the taking of such plants and animals as are permitted by regulations specific to the area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>Watershed Protection. No person shall contaminate in any way whatsoever any watershed or water supply at Tunitas Creek Beach, or shall deposit any urine or fecal material anywhere at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>Water Quality Protection. No person shall wash clothing or cooking utensils, bathe in, or in any other manner pollute the waters at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Geological Features Protection. No person shall destroy, disturb, mutilate or remove earth, sand, gravel, oil, minerals, rocks, or features of caves, or lay, or set off any explosive material or cause to be done or assist in doing any of these things at Tunitas Creek Beach except by permit issued by the County of San Mateo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>Protection of Historical Features. No person shall remove, injure, disfigure, deface or destroy any object of paleontological, archaeological, or historical interest or value at Tunitas Creek Beach or any hiking and riding trail thereto nor shall any person engage in any excavation for said objects without first receiving written permission from the Director, or his/her representatives.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>Domestic Animals. No dogs, cats, fowl or other domesticated animals shall be permitted to at any time to enter or go at large at Tunitas Creek Beach. Nothing in this section shall prohibit a guide dog under the control of a person with a vision or hearing impairment or "police dog" under the control of a peace officer from entering at Tunitas Creek Beach. No person shall release any captured wild animal at Tunitas Creek Beach except authorized public officials pursuant to their duties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>Abandoned Animals. No person shall abandon a dog, cat, fowl or other animal at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>Wildlife. Tunitas Creek Beach is a sanctuary for wildlife. No person shall feed, approach, disturb, frighten, hunt, trap, capture, wound, kill, or disturb the natural habitat of, any wild bird, mammal, reptile, fish, amphibian or invertebrate at Tunitas Creek Beach. This prohibition shall not apply to the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>Action taken by public officials or their employees or agents, within the scope of their authorized duties, to protect the public health and safety.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The taking of fish as permitted by State Fish and Game Regulations.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(3)</num>
          <text>The capturing and/or taking of wildlife for scientific research purposes when done with a permit issued by the County of San Mateo.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>Firearms and Dangerous Weapons. No person shall have in the person's possession at Tunitas Creek Beach, and no person shall fire or discharge, or cause to be fired or discharged, across, in, or into any portion of Tunitas Creek Beach, any gun or firearm, spear, bow and arrow, cross bow, slingshot, air or gas weapon or any other dangerous weapon.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>Loitering After Closing Time. No person shall remain at Tunitas Creek Beach after the posted closing time.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>Alcoholic Beverages. No person shall possess or consume any form of alcoholic beverages at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <text>Private Operations. It shall be unlawful for any person to solicit, sell or peddle any liquids or edibles for human consumption or to distribute circulars or to hawk, peddle or vend any goods, wares or merchandise of any kind at Tunitas Creek Beach, except upon specific concession or permit issued by the County of San Mateo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(p)</num>
        <text>Commercial Filming. No person shall operate a still, motion picture, video or other camera for commercial purposes at Tunitas Creek Beach, except pursuant to a valid written permit from the County authorizing such activity. This section shall not apply to the commercial operation of cameras as part of the bona fide reporting of news.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(q)</num>
        <text>Closed Areas. No person shall enter any road, trail or area at Tunitas Creek Beach that is posted as closed or restricted without permission from the County Parks and Recreation Director.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.070</num>
      <heading>Motor vehicles.</heading>
      <text>No person shall operate any motor vehicle at Tunitas Creek Beach except upon established paved roads or other established paved areas specifically designated and maintained for normal ingress, egress, and parking. This section shall not apply to any emergency or County vehicle, physically handicapped persons operating wheelchairs or similar devices, or to any person acting in compliance with the directions of a Park Ranger or Peace Officer.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.080</num>
      <heading>Parking.</heading>
      <text>No person shall park any motor vehicle at Tunitas Creek Beach, except upon areas designated by the County for parking. No person shall park a motor vehicle, except an authorized emergency vehicle, or when in compliance with the directions of a Peace Officer or Park Ranger, in any of the following places:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>In areas where prohibited by "NO PARKING" signs.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>On any fire trail, road or access.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>On any equestrian or hiking trail. Blocking or obstructing any gate, entrance or exit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>On any beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>In such a manner as to take up more than one "Marked" space in any authorized parking area.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>In any area where such vehicle blocks or obstructs the free flow of traffic. Within 15 feet of a fire hydrant.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Adjacent to any curb painted red.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.090</num>
      <heading>Operation of bicycles; violation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall operate a bicycle at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding <cite path="3.69.010">section 3.69.010</cite> of this Ordinance Code, a violation of the provisions of this section shall be an infraction. Any person to whom a citation is issued for a violation of this <cite path="3.69.090">section 3.69.090</cite> shall be subject to a fine of Fifty Dollars ($50) for a first violation within a period of one year; One Hundred Dollars ($100) for a second violation within a period of one year; and Three Hundred Dollars ($300) for each additional violation within a period of one year.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.100</num>
      <heading>Noise.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Declaration of Noise Policy. It is the County's policy to prohibit unnecessary, excessive, and annoying noises at Tunitas Creek Beach. At excessive levels, noises are detrimental to the health and welfare of persons using Tunitas Creek Beach, and it is in the public interest to proscribe such noises.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Sound Amplifying Equipment. It shall be unlawful for any person to operate any sound amplifying equipment as defined in <cite path="3.68.030|(k)">section 3.68.030(k)</cite> at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Peace and Quiet. It shall be unlawful for any person at Tunitas Creek Beach to use or operate any radio receiving set, musical instrument, machine or device for producing or reproducing sound or any device which produces noise in such a manner as to disturb the reasonable peace, quiet and comfort of persons using Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.110</num>
      <heading>Dangerous activities.</heading>
      <text>No person shall engage in any of the following activities at Tunitas Creek Beach or upon any hiking or riding trail thereto, and in no case shall any person engage in any activity or operate any device recklessly or negligently so as to endanger the life, limb or property of any person:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Use or possess fireworks of any kind.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>Drive, chip, or in any other manner play or practice golf, or hit golf balls.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Operate self-propelled model airplanes, aircraft, helicopters, quadcopters, boats, automobiles, or other unmanned or model craft of any kind or description.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>4.</num>
        <text>Throw, release, or discharge missiles, rockets, or similar projectiles.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>5.</num>
        <text>Hang-glide or parachute.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>6.</num>
        <text>Operate any gas or hot air balloon (other than a toy balloon).</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.120</num>
      <heading>Beaches and swimming areas.</heading>
      <text>No person shall launch any vessel with motor or capable of carrying a motor at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.69.130</num>
      <heading>Smoking prohibited.</heading>
      <text>No person shall engage in smoking, as defined by <cite path="4.96">chapter 4.96</cite> of this Code, at Tunitas Creek Beach.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04778">Ord. No. 04778, 6-27-2017</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.72</num>
    <heading>CHILDREN'S HOMES</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.72.010</num>
      <heading>Permit required.</heading>
      <text>Any person who, without having first obtained a written permit to do so from the Department of Social Services, establishes, maintains, conducts or manages any institution, boarding house, home or other place for the reception or care of children, or who keeps at any such place any child under the age of 16 years, not his relative, apprentice or ward, without legal commitment, or neglects, refuses or omits to comply with the provisions of such permit, is guilty of a misdemeanor.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3395</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 446">Ord. 446, 02/08/37</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.72.020</num>
      <heading>Issuance of permits.</heading>
      <text>The Department of Social Services shall have power to issue permits for such places, and every such permit shall specify the name and residence of the person so undertaking the care of such children and the location of the place where the same are kept and the number of children thereby allowed to be received, boarded or kept therein, and shall be revocable for cause by the said Department of Social Services in any case where the provisions of <cite path="3.72">this chapter</cite> are violated, or in any case where in the opinion of the Department of Social Services, such institution, home, boarding house or other place is being managed, conducted or maintained without regard for the health, comfort or morality of the inmates thereof, or without due regard to proper sanitation or hygiene.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3396</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 446">Ord. 446, 02/08/37</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.72.030</num>
      <heading>Register of children necessary.</heading>
      <text>Every person holding such permit must keep a register, wherein he shall enter the names and ages of all such children and the names and reception and discharge of such children and the reasons therefor, and, also the name and age of every child who is given out, adopted, taken away or indentured from such place to or by any person, together with the name and residence of the person so adopting, taking away or indenturing such child, and within forty-eight hours after such child is so given out, taken away or indentured shall cause a correct copy of the register to be sent to the said Department of Social Services.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3397</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 446">Ord. 446, 02/08/37</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.72.040</num>
      <heading>Inspection of premises.</heading>
      <text>It shall be lawful for the officers and representatives of the said Department of Social Services, at all reasonable times, to enter and inspect the premises wherein such children are so boarded, received and kept, and to call for and inspect the permit and register, and also to see and visit such children.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3398</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 446">Ord. 446, 02/08/37</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.76</num>
    <heading>CONSTRUCTION ON PUBLIC ROADS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.76.010</num>
      <heading>Permit required.</heading>
      <text>Any Town or City or any Sanitary District, Sewer Maintenance District, Water Maintenance District, Public Service Company, Private Corporation or Individual, or any other district, person, corporation not herein specified, before installing pipes, conduits, culverts, cables, catch basins, or any other form of construction, temporary or otherwise, in the public streets or roads in the unincorporated areas of San Mateo County, shall first obtain a permit, with specifications from the Director of Public Works.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3420</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 727">Ord. 727, 03/18/47</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.80</num>
    <heading>TRESPASSING</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.80.010</num>
      <heading>Trespassing prohibited.</heading>
      <text>It shall be unlawful for any person, other than the owner of the property or persons having the permission of the owner, to trespass, loiter, wander, or be upon any lands, public or private, which the Board of Supervisors has hereinafter designated in <cite path="3.80">this chapter</cite> as dangerous premises, and upon which the Director of Public Works, with the consent of the owner or owners of said property, has posted a sign as hereinafter provided.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3425.0</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1462">Ord. 1462, 06/13/61</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.80.020</num>
      <heading>Warning signs.</heading>
      <text>The signs to be posted as herein provided shall be of sufficient size to give reasonable notice to persons in the vicinity that said lands so posted are dangerous premises and shall be substantially in the following form:</text>
      <text>WARNING <br/>THIS PROPERTY IS DESIGNATED AS DANGEROUS PROPERTY UNDER THE ORDINANCES OF THE COUNTY OF SAN MATEO. IT SHALL BE UNLAWFUL TO TRESPASS THEREON WITHOUT THE CONSENT OF THE OWNER</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3425.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1462">Ord. 1462, 06/13/61</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.80.030</num>
      <heading>Posting of warning signs.</heading>
      <text>The warning signs to be posted by the Director of Public Works as herein provided in <cite path="3.80">this chapter</cite> shall be posted in conspicuous places within the property designated as dangerous premises, at intervals of not more than 100 feet and violating trespassers shall be guilty of a misdemeanor.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3425.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1462">Ord. 1462, 06/13/61</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.80.040</num>
      <heading>Dangerous premises defined.</heading>
      <text>For the purpose of <cite path="3.80">this chapter</cite> the Board of Supervisors hereby finds and declares that those lands which are and constitute "dangerous premises" are situated in the unincorporated territory of the County of San Mateo, State of California, and more particularly described as follows:</text>
      <text>All that certain area of land lying westerly of State Highway Route No. 1, between Station D-321 plus 00, said station being at or near a culvert having the marking D-6.10 on a guide post at its inlet end, and Station D-450 plus 00, said station being approximately 350 feet westerly of a culvert having the marking D-8.48 on a guide post at its inlet end; the aforementioned stations having been established by surveys by the State Division of Highways, and being delineated on that certain set of plans prepared by said State Division of Highways, dated May 25, 1936, and entitled "PLAN AND PROFILE OF STATE HIGHWAY IN SAN MATEO COUNTY, BETWEEN FARALLONE CITY AND ROCKAWAY BEACH", a copy of which is on file in the office of the Director of Public Works, in the Court House, Redwood City.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3425.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 1462">Ord. 1462, 06/13/61</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3113">Ord. 3113, 06/16/87</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.82</num>
    <heading>TRESPASSING ON PRIVATE PROPERTY</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.82.010</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.82">this chapter</cite>:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Posted property" means any property at each corner of which, at each entrance to which, a sign is posted three feet above the normal ground level, and said sign is composed of wood, metal or other equally substantial material, the face of which is not less than one square foot in area, and upon which, in legible letters not less than two inches in height, appear the words, "PRIVATE PROPERTY—NO TRESPASS." In addition to the words "PRIVATE PROPERTY—NO TRESPASS," the sign may contain such other words as may be desired, indicating that trespassers are subject to prosecution. Where the area of such property exceeds one acre, the signs shall be posted at intervals of not more than three hundred feet along or near the boundaries thereof.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4312">Ord. 4312, 05/23/06</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.82.020</num>
      <heading>Trespasses upon private property prohibited.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>No person shall remain upon any private property or business premises, after being notified by the owner, owner's agent, lessee or by a peace officer acting at the request of the owner or owner's agent to remove therefrom.</text>
        <para>
          <num>(1)</num>
          <text>For purposes of this section a lessee includes a tenant in lawful possession of real property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>(2)</num>
          <text>The owner or the owner's agent may make a single written request for a peace officer's assistance when the peace officer's assistance in dealing with a trespass is requested. However, such single written request shall cover a period of time of one year and may identify specific dates and times. During such dates and times, a peace officer may act to remove a trespasser as set forth herein without the necessity of the owner or the owner's agent making a separate request on each occasion when the peace officer's assistance in dealing with a trespass is requested.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>No person, without permission, expressed or implied, from the owner, owner's agent or lessee, shall enter upon such private property or business premises after having been notified by the owner, owner's agent or lessee to keep off or keep away therefrom.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>No person shall enter or remain upon posted property without the permission, expressed or implied, of the owner, owner's agent, tenant or lessee of such posted property or premises.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4312">Ord. 4312, 05/23/06</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.82.030</num>
      <heading>Infraction.</heading>
      <text>Any person who violates the provisions of <cite path="3.82">this chapter</cite> is guilty of an infraction punishable by a fine set forth in Government Code section 25132 and any amendments thereto.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 4312">Ord. 4312, 05/23/06</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.88</num>
    <heading>ALARM SYSTEMS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.010</num>
      <heading>Purpose.</heading>
      <text>This ordinance is enacted pursuant to Business and Professions Code section 7592.8. The purpose of this ordinance is to establish rules and regulations concerning the use of alarms in commercial locations in the unincorporated areas of the County, to enhance the effectiveness of these devices, and to minimize law enforcement response to false alarms caused by the improper use or abuse of these systems.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3500</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.020</num>
      <heading>Permit required.</heading>
      <text>No person shall install or operate an alarm system on any commercial premises under his or her control without first obtaining a permit as required by <cite path="3.88">this chapter</cite>. A permit for an alarm system shall be obtained from the Sheriff's Department.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3501</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.030</num>
      <heading>Permit for existing alarm systems.</heading>
      <text>Any person who installed an alarm system on his commercial premises before the effective date of this ordinance shall obtain a permit for the alarm system as required by <cite path="3.88">this chapter</cite> if the alarm system is still in operation. The permit must be obtained within 180 days after the effective date of this ordinance.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3502</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.040</num>
      <heading>Exclusions.</heading>
      <text><cite path="3.88">This chapter</cite> shall not apply to alarm systems in motor vehicles, alarm systems operated by public agencies, alarm systems installed on residential premises, or alarm systems on any premises located within the boundaries of the Broadmoor Police Protection District.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3503</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.050</num>
      <heading>Application form and fee.</heading>
      <text>Each person who installs or operates an alarm system on any commercial premises under his control shall complete and submit to the County Sheriff a permit application on a form containing all information required by the Sheriff. Each person shall pay a fee for processing the permit. The Sheriff shall set the amount of the fee, and the fee shall not exceed $25.00. The permit shall be valid for one year from the date of issuance and may be renewed for successive one-year periods upon payments of an annual renewal fee. The Sheriff shall also set the amount of the renewal fee, which shall not exceed $25.00.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3504</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.060</num>
      <heading>Prohibition.</heading>
      <text>No audible alarm system may emit a sound the same as or similar to sirens used on emergency vehicles or civil defense or fire department stationary sirens.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3505</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.070</num>
      <heading>Requirement for automatic shut off device.</heading>
      <text>No audible alarm system may be operated or installed that does not have a device which automatically shuts off the sound within fifteen minutes after the alarm is activated. If an audible alarm system will not shut off and a responsible party cannot be located to shut if off, the Sheriff may call any alarm service company to shut off the alarm. The alarm user will be billed and must pay for any expense incurred.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3506</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.080</num>
      <heading>Restrictions on automatic calling devices.</heading>
      <text>No alarm system shall utilize an automatic calling device which places a call to any emergency police, fire, or medical service telephone number, other than the number provided by the Sheriff. The alarm user will be provided with a telephone number for automatic calling devices upon obtaining a permit. Only this telephone number shall be used with these devices.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3507</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.090</num>
      <heading>Revocation of permit.</heading>
      <text>The Sheriff may revoke any alarm system permit if he determines that the system does not comply with the provisions of <cite path="3.88">this chapter</cite>. The alarm user will be notified in writing ten (10) working days before the effective date of the revocation. This notice will be sent to the premises upon which the alarm system is located by first class mail and will include a statement of the reasons for the proposed revocation. The revocation of the permit will be effective ten (10) workings days after notice of the revocation is mailed. The alarm user may request in writing that the Sheriff reconsider any decision to revoke an alarm system permit. Such a request must be received by the Sheriff within five (5) working days after the revocation notice is mailed. The alarm user will be given written notification of the results of the review and a statement of the reasons for the action to be taken. The Sheriff may, in his sole discretion, revoke the permit, reinstate the permit, suspend the permit for a reasonable period of time, reinstate the permit with restrictions or additional provisions, and assess a penalty as provided in <cite path="3.88">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3508</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.100</num>
      <heading>False alarms—Service charges and grounds for revocation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The intentional activation of a false alarm will result in the permanent revocation of the alarm permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The activation of a false alarm due to the negligence of the alarm user or authorized operator will result in the assessment of a $25 service charge to the user to defray the cost of responding to the alarm location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>The activation of three false alarms caused by malfunctioning of the alarm system within a calendar year will result in a $25 service charge being assessed to the alarm user to defray the cost of responding to the alarm location.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>A fourth false alarm in a calendar year caused by negligence or malfunctioning will result in revocation of the alarm permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>An alarm permit revoked for false alarms due to malfunctions may be automatically reinstated upon proof from the person servicing the alarm system that it has been repaired and upon payment of a $50 fee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>No fee shall be assessed or sanctions imposed for false alarms activated by storms, electrical failures, natural disasters, acts of God or other events not under the control of the alarm user or the fault of the alarm system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>The permit application form prescribed by the Sheriff shall require the alarm user to provide the names, addresses, and telephone numbers of two persons to respond to the premises when the alarm system is activated. If a responsible party fails to respond to an alarm signal, the Sheriff may revoke the alarm system permit.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>The Sheriff may revoke an alarm permit for failure to pay any charges or fees required under <cite path="3.88">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3509</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.110</num>
      <heading>Infraction.</heading>
      <text>Any person who installs or operates an alarm system on any commercial premises without a valid permit is guilty of an infraction punishable by (a) a fine not exceeding one hundred dollars ($100) for a first violation; (b) a fine not exceeding two hundred dollars ($200) for a second violation within one year; (c) a fine not exceeding five hundred dollars ($500) for each additional violation within one year.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3510</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.88.120</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>"Alarm system" means any device designed to signal the presence of an emergency situation or the commission of a criminal act and to which police or other emergency agencies are expected to respond.</text>
      <text>"Alarm user" means any individual or business using an alarm system.</text>
      <text>"Audible alarm" means any alarm device which when activated generates an audible sound on the premises protected.</text>
      <text>"Automatic calling device" means any device used in conjunction with an alarm system which generates a telephone message upon activation of the alarm system to another location for the purposes of summoning emergency assistance to the premises.</text>
      <text>"Calendar year" means that period of time starting on January 1 and ending on December 31 of any given year.</text>
      <text>"Commercial premises" means any premises except residential premises.</text>
      <text>"False alarm" means an alarm signal necessitating response by the Sheriff where there has been no emergency situation or the commission of a criminal act.</text>
      <text>"Person" means any individual, partnership, corporation or other entity.</text>
      <text>"Residential premises" means single-family or multiple-family dwellings and includes apartments, townhouses, and condominiums.</text>
      <text>"Responsible party" means any person designated by an alarm user as having responsibility for operation and maintenance of an alarm system or as having responsibility for responding to the premises when an alarm system is activated.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3511</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3027">Ord. 3027, 03/12/85</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.100</num>
    <heading>HOME MORTGAGE FINANCING PROGRAM</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.100.010</num>
      <heading>Adoption of Home Mortgage Financing Program.</heading>
      <text>Pursuant to part V of division 31 of the Health and Safety Code of the State of California (the "Act"), commencing with section 52000, and based upon the findings of the Board of Supervisors, the County hereby adopts a home mortgage financing program (the "Program") pursuant to the Act for the purpose of increasing the housing supply for moderate and low-income families in the unincorporated areas of the County and within the incorporated areas of the Cities within the County which cooperate with the County in undertaking the Program.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3910.1</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2787">Ord. 2787, 05/18/82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.100.020</num>
      <heading>Findings.</heading>
      <text>The Board of Supervisors hereby finds and declares that:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Decent housing is an essential motivating force in helping people to achieve self-fulfillment in a free and democratic society;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>A healthy housing market is one in which residents of this state have a choice of housing opportunities and one in which the housing consumer may effectively choose within the free market;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>There exists within the County a shortage of housing available to moderate and low-income persons, as such persons are now or hereafter defined by the provisions of the Act, and that this shortage is exacerbated during periods of rising interest rates, particularly as high interest rates have the effect of diminishing the number of otherwise creditworthy buyers from qualifying for private sector mortgage capital sources, and in order to remedy this adverse effect of potential homebuyers on the lower end of the purchasing spectrum, it is necessary to implement a public program to reduce the cost of mortgage financing for single-family purchases for those persons unable to compete for mortgage financing in the conventional mortgage market; and</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>It is necessary, in order to implement a public program to reduce the cost of mortgage financing to authorize long-term, low-interest mortgages to persons not presently eligible for financing through private sector lending institutions to finance construction, rehabilitation and acquisition of homes, and in order to finance the Program, to issue mortgage revenue bonds to fund the Program.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3910.2</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2787">Ord. 2787, 05/18/82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.100.030</num>
      <heading>Condominium conversions.</heading>
      <text>Only condominium conversion projects for which a final subdivision map has been recorded no later than April 30, 1982, may be financed under this program. No other condominium conversion projects shall be financed under the program.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3910.3</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2787">Ord. 2787, 05/18/82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.100.040</num>
      <heading>Regulations establishing criteria for qualification of lending institutions.</heading>
      <text>Pursuant to section 52020 of the Act, the County hereby adopts the following criteria for qualification of lending institutions for the program:</text>
      <para>
        <num>1.</num>
        <text>Such lending institution shall be seller/servicer approved by either the Federal National Mortgage Association or the Federal Home Loan Mortgage Corporation;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>2.</num>
        <text>The lending institution shall have demonstrated the capacity to originate and service home mortgages of the nature and in the number proposed for the program, as shown by information filed with respect to invitations distributed by the County Director of Housing and Community Development;</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>3.</num>
        <text>Final selection of a qualified lending institution shall be based upon the foregoing and the agreement of the lending institution to provide such services at a reasonable cost most advantageous to the homebuyers participating in the program.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3910.4</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 2787">Ord. 2787, 05/18/82</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.104</num>
    <heading>DISCRIMINATION</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.010</num>
      <heading>Findings.</heading>
      <text>After public hearings and receipt of testimony, the Board of Supervisors of the County of San Mateo finds and declares:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>That the medical condition described as Acquired Immune Deficiency Syndrome and commonly known as AIDS is a deadly disease caused by infection by a known organism (Human Immuno-Depressant Virus) which has the potential to affect every segment of our County's population.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>That the opinion of the medical and scientific community is that persons with AIDS, or any medical signs or symptoms related thereto, have been infected by the Human Immuno-Depressant Virus, which attacks and cripples the body's immune system.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>That such destruction of the host immune system results in a variety of illnesses which debilitate the body resulting in a wide spectrum of clinical disease causing a high mortality rate among those so infected.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>That the spread of the virus is through the exchange of blood, blood products, and semen between individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>That transmission of this disease is also one of maternal transmission, from an infected mother to her infant, either during fetal development or at the time of birth.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>That the spread of this virus is due to specific known behaviors and actions and that there is no medical evidence of such infection occurring by casual contact.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>That the public health danger presented by this virus in all of its manifestations is caused by a lengthy asymptomatic period of infection during which an apparently healthy individual may spread the disease to other individuals.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>That medical studies of family groups in which one or more persons have been known to be infected by the virus show no spread of the virus other than by sexual intimacy or through the exchange of blood and blood products (including from mother to fetus).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>That the HIV virus is a fragile virus which can thrive only in favorable conditions and can be protected against by the application of regular practices of hygiene, such as the use of chlorine in swimming pools and spas, the use of household bleach when washing garments or cleaning contaminated surfaces and hand and/or body washing with soap and water.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>That those persons currently infected with this virus, in all of its phases and manifestations, represent a segment of our population particularly victimized due to the nature of this disease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>That the spread of this disease, in the opinion of the medical community, will increase at a high rate within our County for the foreseeable future.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>That discrimination against victims of this virus exists within the County of San Mateo.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>That such discrimination cuts across all racial, ethnic, cultural, and economic lines.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>That such discrimination cuts across all age groups, including infants who may be especially disenfranchised by this disease.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <text>That existing state and federal restraints on such arbitrary discrimination are inadequate to meet the particular problems of this county.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3950</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.020</num>
      <heading>Employment.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Prohibited Activity. Any of the following acts shall constitute discrimination and are unlawful and prohibited when they are done as a result of the fact, in whole or in part, that a person has AIDS or associated conditions as defined by section 3.104.090 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>By an Employer. To fail or refuse to hire, or to discharge any individual; to discriminate against any individual with respect to compensation, terms, conditions, or privileges or employment, including promotion; or to limit, segregate or classify employees in any way which would deprive or tend to deprive any individual of employment opportunities, or otherwise adversely affect his/her status as an employee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>By an Employment Agency. To fail or refuse to refer for employment any individual; or otherwise to discriminate against any individual.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>By a Labor Organization. To exclude or expel from its membership or to otherwise discriminate against any individual; or to limit, segregate or classify its membership; or to classify or fail or refuse to refer for employment any individual in any way which would deprive or tend to deprive such individual of employment opportunities, or would limit such employment opportunities, or otherwise adversely affect his/her status as an employee or as an applicant for employment.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>By an Employer, Employment Agency, or Labor Organization.</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>To discriminate against any individual in admission to, or employment in, any program established to provide apprenticeship or other training or retraining, including any on-the-job training program.</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>To print, publish, advertise, or disseminate in any way, or cause to be printed, published, advertised, or disseminated in any way, any notice or advertisement with respect to employment, membership in, or any classification or referral for employment or training by any such organization, which indicates an unlawful discriminatory act or preference.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Bona fide Occupational Qualification Not Discrimination.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Nothing contained in this section shall be deemed to prohibit selection or rejection based upon a bona fide occupational qualification, which is defined as a condition or a qualification that relates to a person's ability or inability to discharge the duties of a particular job, and the capacity of an individual to perform his or her duties without endangering his or her health or safety, or the health or safety of others.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>If a party asserts that an otherwise discriminatory practice is justified as a bonafide occupational qualification, the following factors shall be considered.</text>
          <para>
            <num>a.</num>
            <text>Whether the discrimination is in fact a necessary result of a bona fide occupational qualification; and</text>
          </para>
          <para>
            <num>b.</num>
            <text>Whether there exists no less discriminatory means of satisfying the occupational qualification.</text>
          </para>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Exceptions. Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit any act specifically authorized by the laws of the State of California or any actions taken by or under the direction of the San Mateo County Department of Health Services in order to protect the public health.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3951</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.030</num>
      <heading>Housing.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Prohibited Activity. Any of the following acts shall constitute discrimination and are unlawful and prohibited when they are done as a result of the fact, in whole or in part, that a person has AIDS or any of the associated conditions as defined by section 3.104.090 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>To interrupt, terminate, or fail or refuse to initiate or conduct any transaction in real property, including but not limited to the rental thereof; to require different terms for such transaction; or falsely to represent that an interest in real property is not available for transaction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>To include in the terms or conditions of a transaction in real property any clause, condition, or restriction.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>To refuse to lend money, guarantee the loan of money, accept a deed of trust or mortgage, or otherwise refuse to make available funds for the purchase, acquisition, construction, alteration, rehabilitation, repair, or maintenance of real property; or impose conditions on such financing; or refuse to provide title or other insurance relating to the ownership or use of any interest in real property.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>To refuse or restrict facilities, services, repairs, or improvement for any tenant or lessee.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>To make, print, publish, advertise, or disseminate in any way, or cause to be made, printed or published, advertised or disseminated in any way, any notice, statement or advertisement with respect to a transaction or proposed transaction in real property, or with respect to financing related to any such transaction, which unlawfully indicates preference, limitation or discrimination based on AIDS.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Exceptions.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Nothing in this section shall be deemed to permit any rental or occupancy of any dwelling unit or commercial space otherwise prohibited by law.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit any act specifically authorized by the laws of the State of California or any actions taken by or under the direction of the San Mateo County Department of Health Services in order to protect the public health.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3952</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.040</num>
      <heading>Business establishments and public accommodations.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Prohibited Activity. The denial of the full and equal enjoyment of goods, services, facilities, privileges, advantages, and accommodations of any business establishment or public accommodation shall constitute discrimination and is unlawful and prohibited when done as a result of the fact, in whole or in part, that a person has AIDS or any of the associated conditions as defined by section 3.104.090 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Advertising. No person shall make, print, publish, advertise, or disseminate in any way any notice, statement, or advertisement with respect to any business establishment or public accommodation which indicates that a person is doing or will do anything which is defined by this ordinance as discrimination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>Exceptions. Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit any act specifically authorized by the laws of the State of California or any actions taken by or under the direction of the San Mateo County Department of Health Services in order to protect the public health.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3953</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.050</num>
      <heading>County facilities and services.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The denial of the full and equal enjoyment, or the imposition of different terms or conditions on the availability, of any of the following constitutes discrimination and is unlawful and prohibited when done as a result of the fact, in whole or in part, that a person has AIDS or any of the associated conditions as defined by section 3.104.090 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>Use of any County facility or County service.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Any service, program or facility wholly or partially funded or otherwise supported by the County of San Mateo.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit any act which is specifically authorized by the laws of the State of California or any actions taken by or under the direction of the San Mateo County Department of Health Services in order to protect the public health.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3954</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.060</num>
      <heading>Association and retaliation.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Association. It shall be discrimination and is unlawful and prohibited for any person to do any of the acts described in sections 3.104.020 through 3.104.050 of the Ordinance Code, as a result of the fact that a person associates with anyone who has AIDS or any of the associated conditions as defined by section 3.104.090 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Retaliation. It shall be discrimination for any person to do any of the acts described in section 3.104.020 through 3.104.050 of the Ordinance Code or to retaliate against a person because a person:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>has opposed any act or practice defined as discrimination by sections 3.104.020 through 3.104.050 of this Ordinance Code;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>has supported this ordinance and its enforcement;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>has filed an allegation pursuant to section 3.104.080 of this Ordinance Code with the San Mateo Department of Health Services;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>has assisted, or participated in any way in any mediation or proceeding specified in section 3.104.080 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3955</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.070</num>
      <heading>Testing.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>No person shall require another to take any test or undergo any medical procedure designed to show or to help to show that a person has AIDS or any of the associated conditions defined by section 3.104.090 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Nothing in this section shall be construed to prohibit any act specifically authorized by the laws of the State of California or any actions taken by or under the direction of the San Mateo County Department of Health Services in order to protect the public health.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3956</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.080</num>
      <heading>Investigation, mediation and resolution of allegations of discrimination.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>Any person who believes that he or she has been discriminated against as defined by sections 3.104.020 through 3.104.080 of this Ordinance Code may file an allegation with the County of San Mateo Department of Health Services.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>Upon receipt of any such allegation, the Department of Health Services is authorized to investigate and mediate the allegation, and to seek resolution of the allegation, while maintaining all necessary confidentiality required by law. The efforts of the department pursuant to this section are limited to endeavors at investigation, conference, conciliation, and persuasion.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>In investigating, mediating and resolving such allegations of discrimination, the Department of Health Services by and through the Director of Health Services may establish an AIDS Task Force whose members will be determined by the Director of Health Services of San Mateo County and assign such investigation, mediation and resolution functions to the AIDS Task Force.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3957</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.090</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>As used in <cite path="3.104">this chapter</cite>, the following words or phrases shall have the meanings indicated;</text>
      <para>
        <num>A.</num>
        <text>The words "AIDS" shall be defined according to the guidelines established by the U.S. Department of Health and Human Services Center for Disease Control. Associated conditions shall mean AIDS Related Complex (ARC) or a positive human immuno depressant virus (HIV) test.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>B.</num>
        <text>The phrase "business establishment" shall mean any entity, however organized, which furnishes goods or services to the general public. An otherwise qualifying establishment which has membership requirements is considered to furnish services to the general public if its membership requirements consist only of payment of fees or consist of requirements according to which the majority of adult residents of this County could qualify.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>C.</num>
        <text>The word "person" as used in <cite path="3.104">this chapter</cite> shall mean any individual, person, firm, corporation, or other organization or group of persons however organized.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3958</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.100</num>
      <heading>Severability.</heading>
      <text>If any part or provision of <cite path="3.104">this chapter</cite>, or the application thereof to any person or circumstances is held invalid, the remainder of the chapter, including the application of such part or provision to other persons or circumstances, shall not be affected thereby and shall continue in full force and effect. To this end, provisions of <cite path="3.104">this chapter</cite> are severable.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3959</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.104.110</num>
      <heading>Application to the unincorporated area county of San Mateo.</heading>
      <text>All provisions of this ordinance apply to unincorporated areas of the County of San Mateo. However, the investigation, mediation and resolution services authorized by section 3.104.080 may be provided any where in the County when in the judgment of the Director of Health Services such services may be beneficial in resolving such allegations of discrimination as defined by sections 3.104.020 through 3.104.080 of this Ordinance Code.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History">Prior code § 3960</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 3140">Ord. 3140, 04/12/88</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
  <container>
    <prefix>Chapter</prefix>
    <num>3.108</num>
    <heading>PROPERTY OWNER OBLIGATIONS WITH RESPECT TO TENANTS DISPLACED FROM UNSAFE OR SUBSTANDARD UNITS</heading>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.010</num>
      <heading>Title.</heading>
      <text><cite path="3.108">This chapter</cite> shall be known as Property Owner Obligations With Respect to Tenants Displaced from Unsafe or Substandard Units.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.020</num>
      <heading>Definitions.</heading>
      <text>For the purposes of this <cite path="3.10">chapter 3.10</cite>8, the following words and phrases shall have the meanings set forth herein:</text>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>"Code enforcement activities" are activities initiated by the County of San Mateo to determine the condition and/or legal conformity or nonconformity of a dwelling and to require the property owner to make necessary repairs to the dwelling, to vacate the dwelling, or to take other action as necessary to bring the dwelling into compliance with applicable state or local zoning, building, and/or housing standards, and/or other technical codes adopted and enforced by the County for existing residential properties.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>"Declaration of substandard condition" means a declaration, notice, or order executed by an Enforcement Officer under the authority of the applicable provision of law declaring that a dwelling is substandard.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>"Definitive steps" means specific actions taken by a tenant household indicating an intent to move from a dwelling or room during an expected displacement period, such as entering into contracts or incurring expenses directly related to the anticipated move from the dwelling or room, and which can be substantiated with reasonably probative documentation (such as bills, invoices, rental agreements, estimates, etc.).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>"Dwelling" means any structure that a person uses as a place of permanent or customary abode in the unincorporated area of the County, including, but not limited to, a single-family dwelling, a unit in multifamily or multipurpose dwelling, a unit of a condominium or cooperative housing project, a mobile home as herein defined, a garage or shed, or any other unit or property that is considered to be real property under state law. A dwelling is any structure that is actually used for residential purposes regardless of whether the structure is decent, safe or sanitary and regardless of whether the actual residential use is legally permitted or conforming under any applicable laws or regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>"Department" means the San Mateo County Planning and Building Department.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>"Director" means the head of the Department, or his or her designee.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>"Enforcement Officer" means any County employee or agent of the County whose position requires enforcement of any provision of the San Mateo County Ordinance Code, any County ordinance or any state law or regulation related to zoning, building or housing standards, and/or other technical codes adopted by the County for existing residential properties including, but not limited to, code compliance officers, building officials and environmental health specialists.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>"Mobile home" means a mobile home as defined in Section 798.3 of the California Civil Code.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(i)</num>
        <text>"Noncomplying dwelling or room" means a dwelling or room in the unincorporated area of the County which has been found or determined by an Enforcement Officer to be substandard, blighted, unsafe, a public nuisance, a drug nuisance, or otherwise not in conformity with applicable state or local zoning, building and/or housing standards and/or other technical codes adopted and enforced by the County for existing residential properties; and "noncomplying condition" or "noncompliance" means any physical condition or use with respect to the dwelling or room that contributes to such finding or determination.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(j)</num>
        <text>"Notice to abate life-threatening condition" means a notice and/or order to abate a substandard or noncomplying condition issued by the County pursuant to its code enforcement activities, however such notice or order is denominated, that indicates on its face that a life threatening condition is present.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(k)</num>
        <text>"Notice to vacate" means a notice and/or order, however denominated, issued by the County or a court of competent jurisdiction to a property owner and/or a tenant household pursuant to the County's code enforcement activities requiring that a dwelling or room be vacated, either immediately or at some future specified time, as a result of a determination that such dwelling or room fails to comply with applicable building, housing, zoning, or other code standards. For purposes of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, a "Notice to Vacate" includes a complaint or action filed by the County with a court of competent jurisdiction and served on the property owner pursuant to the County's code enforcement activities whereby the County asks for vacation of the property as requested relief.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(l)</num>
        <text>"Permanent displacement" means the vacating of a dwelling or room by a tenant household due to code enforcement activities when that dwelling or room (or an equivalent dwelling or room in the building), in the judgment of the Enforcement Officer, cannot foreseeably be brought into code compliance or will not otherwise be available for re-occupancy by the tenant household within ninety (90) days from the date of vacating; or when the tenant household and the property owner have agreed that the displacement shall be permanent.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(m)</num>
        <text>"Property owner" means a person, persons, corporation, partnership, limited liability company, or any other entity holding fee title to the subject real property. In the case of multiple ownership of the subject real property, "property owner" means each entity holding any portion of the fee interest in the property and the property owner's obligations in <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> shall be joint and several as to each property owner.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(n)</num>
        <text>"Room" means an unsubdivided portion of the interior of a dwelling in the unincorporated area of the County which is used for the purpose of sleeping, and is occupied by a tenant household for at least thirty (30) consecutive days. This includes, but is not limited to, a single room occupancy (SRO) living space. This definition applies to any space that is actually used for residential purposes regardless of whether the structure is decent, safe or sanitary and regardless of whether the actual residential use is legally permitted or conforming under any applicable laws or regulations.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(o)</num>
        <text>"Temporary displacement" means the vacating of a dwelling or room by a tenant household due to code enforcement activities when that dwelling or room (or an equivalent dwelling or room in the same building) will foreseeably be brought into code compliance and be available for re-occupancy by the tenant household within ninety (90) days from the date of vacating; or when the tenant household and property owner have otherwise agreed that the displacement shall be considered temporary.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(p)</num>
        <text>"Tenant household" means one or more individuals who rent or lease a dwelling or room as their primary residence and who share living expenses.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.030</num>
      <heading>Tenant eligibility for relocation payments.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>A tenant household shall be eligible for relocation payments from a property owner under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> if the tenant household is displaced from its dwelling or room due to the County's code enforcement activities. For purposes of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, a tenant household shall be deemed to be displaced from its dwelling or room due to code enforcement activities in either of the following circumstances:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The tenant household receives a notice from the property owner requiring the household to vacate or quit the dwelling or room at any time after the County or a court has issued a notice to vacate, notice to abate life-threatening condition or a declaration of substandard condition covering that dwelling or room; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The tenant household vacates its dwelling or room (whether or not the property owner requires vacation) after (a) the County or a court has issued a notice to vacate, notice to abate life-threatening condition, or declaration of substandard condition covering that dwelling or room, and (b) the abatement period has expired without correction of the noncomplying condition (if a time period to abate the noncomplying condition is specified in such notice or declaration and the County or court does not order earlier vacation).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding subsection (a) above, a tenant household shall not be deemed displaced due to code enforcement activities in any of the following cases:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>The property owner demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Director that vacation of the dwelling or room was due primarily to a cause other than either (a) the noncomplying condition, (b) the County's or court's determination that the dwelling or room was a noncomplying dwelling or room, or (c) the need to make repairs to rectify any noncomplying condition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The property owner demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Director that the noncomplying condition was created by the tenant household or the tenant household's guests or invitees, and was not created by the property owner or the property owner's agent, or that the condition giving rise to the code enforcement activities existed at the time that the tenant household occupied the dwelling or room and that the tenant household occupied the dwelling or room for the purpose of receiving relocation benefits;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The property owner demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Director that the tenant household unreasonably prevented the property owner or the property owner's agent from undertaking maintenance or repairs that would have prevented or rectified the noncomplying condition;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>All noncomplying conditions are corrected, as determined by the County, prior to the time the tenant household has taken definitive steps to move from the dwelling or room;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>5.</num>
          <text>The notice to vacate, notice to abate life-threatening condition, or declaration of substandard condition is rescinded or withdrawn by the County or the court or is overturned on appeal prior to the time the tenant household has taken definitive steps to move from the dwelling or room;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>6.</num>
          <text>The property owner offers, in writing, to move the tenant household immediately into a replacement dwelling or room in the same building, and all of the following are true: (a) the replacement dwelling or room is at least substantially comparable in size, condition and amenities to the formerly occupied dwelling or room; (b) the replacement dwelling or room complies with all applicable zoning, building and housing codes; (c) the replacement rent is no greater than the rent charged for the formerly occupied dwelling or room; and (d) the offer was made prior to the time the tenant household has taken definitive steps to move; or</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>7.</num>
          <text>The tenant household is required to vacate the dwelling or room due solely to damage resulting from an earthquake, fire, flood, natural disaster, civil disturbance, or accident outside the control of the property owner, if (a) the vacation is required within six months of such event, and (b) the property owner demonstrates to the satisfaction of the Director that such damage was not caused by the acts or the negligence of the property owner or by a preexisting condition in the building in violation of applicable building, housing, fire, or other health and safety codes.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Any provision of a lease or rental agreement for a dwelling or room in which the tenant household agrees to modify or waive any of its rights under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, including its rights to relocation payments, shall be void as contrary to public policy.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.040</num>
      <heading>County notices to property owners.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>An Enforcement Officer or other authorized official, along with issuance of any notice to vacate, notice to abate life-threatening condition, or declaration of substandard condition to a property owner covering a dwelling or room shall inform the property owner that any tenant household that vacates said dwelling or room may be eligible for relocation payments from the property owner, that failure to make required relocation payments to eligible tenant households before vacation may result in the County making payments on behalf of the property owner, and that failure to reimburse the County for all relocation payments made and other costs incurred may result in a lien being placed on the property. Following issuance of any such notice or declaration and expiration of the period to abate the noncomplying condition (if an abatement period is specified in any such notice or declaration), the County shall also use reasonable efforts to deliver information to each affected tenant household in the building regarding the relocation benefits and assistance, if any, to which the tenant household may be entitled.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Failure by the County to supply or attempt to supply any of the information or notices provided for in <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> shall not affect the validity of any code enforcement notice, order, or action, nor shall any such failure impact any property owner's obligation to abate any noncomplying conditions or provide relocation assistance as required under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.050</num>
      <heading>Property owners' notices to tenants.</heading>
      <text>Any notice from a property owner to an eligible tenant household to vacate or quit a dwelling or room following the issuance of a notice to vacate, notice to abate a life threatening condition, or declaration of substandard condition must set forth the reasons for the need to vacate, the tenant household's entitlement to relocation payments from the property owner, the tenant household's right to reoccupancy following completion of repairs (if the property is one to be repaired), and the estimated date for reoccupancy. The property owner shall send a copy of all notices to the Enforcement Officer issuing the notice on behalf of the County.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.060</num>
      <heading>Relocation payments by property owners.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The property owner shall be responsible for providing relocation payments, in the amounts specified in section 3.108.090, to an eligible tenant household in the form and manner prescribed in <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Except as set forth in section 3.108.060(e), in the case of permanent displacement, the property owner shall make the relocation payment directly to an eligible tenant household no later than ten (10) days before the expected vacation date of the dwelling or room specified in either a County or court notice or order or the property owner's notice to vacate pursuant to sections 3.108.040 and 3.108.050, whichever date is earliest in the event of multiple notices. If less than ten (10) days' advance notice of vacation is given, or no vacation date is specified in such notice or order, then the payment by the property owner to the tenant household shall be made no later than the actual time of vacation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>If an eligible tenant household vacates a dwelling or room on its own initiative pursuant to section 3.108.030(a)(2) in response to a notice to abate life-threatening condition or declaration of substandard condition issued by the County (rather than in response to a notice to vacate by the County, a court or a property owner), and if that tenant household has not given advance notice to the property owner of its intention to vacate, then the payment by the property owner to the tenant household shall be made no later than ten (10) days after written demand for such payment is made by the tenant household to the property owner; provided, however, that in such case, such a demand must be made in writing by the tenant household within thirty (30) days following the actual vacation of the dwelling or room.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>In the case of temporary displacement, the property owner shall make the payment directly to an eligible tenant household within five (5) days after the tenant household has submitted reasonably probative documentation (such as bills, invoices, rental agreements, estimates, etc.) to the property owner of the actual moving and temporary housing expenses the tenant household will incur or has incurred as a result of the temporary displacement during the expected displacement period.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(e)</num>
        <text>If the property owner and the tenant household agree in writing that a displacement initially treated as a temporary displacement is to be a permanent displacement, the property owner shall provide the tenant household relocation payments for temporary displacement required under section 3.108.090(b) within the period required under section 3.108.060(d), as well as relocation payments for permanent displacement required under section 3.108.090(a) within ten (10) days after the displacement is determined, in writing, to be a permanent displacement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(f)</num>
        <text>The obligation of the property owner to deliver relocation payments to a tenant household shall be suspended pending the outcome of an appeal pursuant to section 3.108.110 of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, if the property owner has made a timely request for appeal.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(g)</num>
        <text>Notwithstanding other provisions of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, a tenant household shall not be required to vacate the dwelling or room until the required relocation payment has been made and any appeal requested by the property owner has been concluded, unless (1) the Enforcement Officer has determined for health and safety reasons that vacation must occur sooner; or (2) the property owner has complied with the provisions of California Government Code Section 7060, et seq., to withdraw such dwelling or room from rental or lease. However, a property owner remains liable for payment of relocation payments to eligible tenant households under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> notwithstanding the applicability of the exceptions above in clauses (1) and (2).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(h)</num>
        <text>The property owner shall also be responsible for reimbursing the County for any relocation payments made and costs incurred by the County pursuant to the provisions of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, including pursuant to section 3.108.070.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.070</num>
      <heading>Relocation payments by County chargeable to property owners.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>The County, in its sole discretion and subject to funding availability, may make any of the payments required of a property owner under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, including advancing eligible tenant household(s) reimbursable "moving expenses" and "temporary housing accommodations costs" as each of these terms are defined below in section 3.108.090(b). Such payments shall continue to be an obligation of the property owner and shall be reimbursed by the property owner to the County. The County may consider making such payments in its own discretion or if a tenant household makes a written request to the Department following a property owner's failure to pay the required payments within the period mandated under section 3.108.060, but in no event later than sixty (60) days following the tenant household's vacation of the dwelling or room. Prior to any County payment to a tenant household, the Director shall make a determination regarding the eligibility of the tenant household for relocation payments. The Department will make reasonable efforts to contact a representative of the property owner prior to making the determination or authorizing the County's payment. However, failure to give prior notice to the property owner shall not relieve the property owner of any obligations under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>When the County makes any relocation payments that are the responsibility of the property owner under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, the County shall bill the property owner for the amount of payment, plus any administrative and other direct and/or indirect costs that it would not have incurred but for the failure of the owner to make the required payment. The County Manager, in consultation with the County Counsel, shall have the discretion to reduce the amount of any required reimbursement from a property owner to the County in cases where the factual and legal circumstances warrant such a reduction. The property owner shall reimburse the County within five (5) days of receipt of billing from the County. If the property owner does not make full and timely payment to the County, the County is entitled to recover an additional amount equal to the sum of one-half the amount paid by the County on the property owner's behalf, but not to exceed ten thousand dollars ($10,000.00), as a penalty for failure to make timely payment. The County may also record a lien on the subject property with the County Recorder and shall provide notice of such lien to the property owner and to the County Assessor. The form of such lien and the manner of enforcement and collection shall be as authorized by state or local law. Alternatively, the County may include the unreimbursed amount in any other lien placed on the property by the County to secure payment of enforcement costs. Notwithstanding the above, the intent of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> is to place primary responsibility for making relocation payments to displaced tenant households on those property owners who are responsible for code violations, and nothing in this section is intended to relieve or release any such property owner from this responsibility.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.080</num>
      <heading>Tenant households' return rights.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>An eligible tenant household who has experienced temporary or permanent displacement from its dwelling or room due to code enforcement activities shall have the right to return to that dwelling or room, or, if this is not possible, to move into an equivalent dwelling or room in the same building if there is an equivalent dwelling or room owned by the same owner, if and when the dwelling or room is ready for occupancy and under the same terms and conditions that applied to the tenancy prior to the period of displacement. If a tenant household intends to exercise this right, it must inform the property owner in writing of its current address at all times during the period of displacement.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>The property owner shall notify the eligible relocated tenant household at least thirty (30) days in advance by certified mail of the availability of the dwelling or room. If a shorter notice is given and the tenant household indicates that it wishes to return, the dwelling or room must be held vacant at no cost to the household for a period no less than thirty-five (35) days after the mailing of the notice of availability. The notice shall provide that within seven (7) days of receipt of notice of availability of the dwelling or room, a tenant household wishing to return must notify the property owner in writing of this election.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>If a tenant household wishing to return to the dwelling or room is required to pay a security deposit, the tenant household must be permitted sufficient time to obtain a refund of any deposit paid to obtain replacement housing during the period of relocation.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>This return right is in addition to an eligible tenant household's entitlement to monetary relocation payments from the property owner under the terms of this <cite path="3.10">chapter 3.10</cite>8, and the exercise of this option by a tenant shall not affect the household's eligibility for such payments.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.090</num>
      <heading>Amount of relocation payments.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Permanent displacement. An eligible tenant household that will experience permanent displacement as defined above shall receive a monetary relocation payment from the property owner equal to three times the current monthly United States Department of Housing and Urban Development (HUD) Fair Market Rent for a unit of comparable size and type to the dwelling or room from which the displacement occurs, plus a payment not to exceed one thousand dollars ($1,000.00) for actual moving costs and related expenses incurred by the tenant household and substantiated by reasonably probative documentation. The property owner shall treat any non-complying dwelling or room that does not have one or more separate bedrooms as an "efficiency unit" for purposes of determining the applicable HUD Fair Market Rent and calculating the required monetary relocation payment on that basis. In addition, the tenant household is entitled to a refund and/or accounting for any security deposit held by the property owner pursuant to California Civil Code Section 1950.5. For purposes of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, "HUD Fair Market Rent" means the amount specified in the schedule of Fair Market Rents for existing housing published by the U.S. Department of Housing and Urban Development under Section 8 of the United States Housing Act of 1937, as amended, applicable to the County of San Mateo and current as of the date the County or court issues the notice to vacate, notice to abate life-threatening condition, or declaration of substandard condition.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Temporary displacement. An eligible tenant household that will experience temporary displacement as defined above shall receive monetary relocation payment or payments from the property owner to cover the tenant household's actual and reasonable moving expenses and temporary housing accommodations costs incurred as a result of the temporary displacement. "Moving expenses" shall include the cost of removing, transporting, and/or storing the tenant household's personal property during the displacement period, and "temporary housing accommodations costs" shall include the cost of rental payments and hotel or motel payments during the displacement period. Except as provided in section 3.108.060(e), in no event shall the property owner be liable for making payments in excess of the amount the tenant household would receive in the case of permanent displacement under section 3.108.090(a).</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Immediate vacation. When the condition of a dwelling or room is a danger to the public health and safety such that the County requires immediate vacation, i.e., vacation with less than thirty (30) days advance notice either from the County or from the property owner to the tenant household of the need to vacate, an eligible tenant household displaced from such a dwelling or room shall be entitled to an additional payment from the property owner in the amount of one thousand dollars ($1,000.00), in addition to the amounts set forth above. Such additional payment is intended to compensate the tenant household for the additional costs associated with short-notice moves and the added inconvenience of such moves.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(d)</num>
        <text>Payments for relocation shall not be considered by the County as income or assets for any government benefits program.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.100</num>
      <heading>Infraction.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any person violating any provision or failing to comply with any of the requirements of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> shall be guilty of an infraction and shall be punishable by the following:</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>A fine not exceeding one hundred dollars ($100.00) for a first violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>A fine not exceeding two hundred dollars ($200.00) for a second violation;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>A fine not exceeding three hundred dollars ($300.00) for each additional violation within one year;</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>4.</num>
          <text>Each person shall be guilty of a separate offense for each and every day during any portion of which said violation is committed.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.110</num>
      <heading>Appeals process.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Written appeal.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>A property owner may contest an order to make relocation payments or a notice of penalty or fine assessed <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> by submitting an appeal in writing together with a processing fee listed in the County's fee schedule. The appeal shall set forth the factual basis for disputing the order to pay relocation benefits or the notice of penalty or fine.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>Appeals must be addressed to the Director, and must be received within ten (10) days of the date appearing on the order to pay relocation benefits or the notice of penalty or fine. A copy of the appeal must be provided by the property owner to any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal on or by the same date that the appeal is received by the Director.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Unless the property owner has requested a hearing pursuant to section 3.108.110(b), after reviewing the appeal, the Director shall prepare a written decision and send it to the property owner and any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal via certified mail or personal delivery. The decision of the Director shall constitute the final decision of the County with no additional administrative right to appeal. To the extent allowed by law, the decision and the order to pay relocation benefits or notice of penalty or fine shall have the same force and effect as a resolution of the County Board of Supervisors for the purpose of filing a lien, special assessment, or for pursuing any other method of collection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Request for hearing; hearing procedure.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>If a property owner desires a hearing on an appeal, a request for hearing must be made at the time the written appeal is submitted. If a hearing is requested, an independent Hearing Officer will be appointed. Any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal shall have the right to attend and participate in the hearing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>The appeal hearing shall be set for a date within thirty (30) days from the date that the appeal is filed, unless the Director determines that good cause exists for an extension of time. The property owner and any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal shall receive notice of the time and place at least fifteen (15) days prior to the hearing unless the Director determined, in writing, that the matter is urgent, in which case the property owner and tenant households shall receive at least five (5) days prior notice of the hearing.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>Documentary evidence and names of potential witnesses shall be provided by the Enforcement Officer, the property owner and any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal to the Hearing Officer and the opposing party at least five (5) days prior to the appeal hearing or as soon as practicable prior to the hearing. At the hearing, the property owner and any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal shall be given the opportunity to testify and to present evidence concerning the order to pay relocation benefits or the notice of penalty or fine. The failure of the property owner to appear at the appeal hearing shall constitute a forfeiture of the fine or penalty (if applicable).</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(c)</num>
        <text>Hearing officer's decision.</text>
        <para>
          <num>1.</num>
          <text>After considering all of the testimony and evidence submitted at the hearing, the Hearing Officer shall issue a written decision to uphold or cancel all or part of the order to pay relocation benefits or the notice of penalty or fine and shall state the reasons for that decision. The decision of the Hearing Officer shall include findings regarding the evidence in the record and submitted at the hearing, as well as the existence of any proper grounds for the order to pay relocation benefits or the notice of penalty or fine. A copy of the Hearing Officer's written decision shall be provided to the property owner as well as any tenant household(s) directly affected by the appeal.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>2.</num>
          <text>If the Hearing Officer determines that the order to pay relocation benefits or the notice of penalty or fine should be upheld, then the property owner shall pay the appropriate sum(s) to the tenant household and/or the County within ten (10) days after the property owner's receipt of the Hearing Officer's written decision.</text>
        </para>
        <para>
          <num>3.</num>
          <text>The decision of the Hearing Officer shall be the final decision of the County with no additional administrative right to appeal. To the extent allowed by law, the decision and the order to pay relocation benefits or notice of penalty or fine shall have the same force and effect as a resolution of the County Board of Supervisors for the purpose of filing a lien, special assessment, or for pursuing any other method of collection.</text>
        </para>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.120</num>
      <heading>Retaliation is barred.</heading>
      <text>No property owner shall take any action in retaliation against any member of a tenant household for exercising rights granted under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.130</num>
      <heading>Private right of action.</heading>
      <para>
        <num>(a)</num>
        <text>Any tenant household that believes that the provisions of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> have been violated shall have the right to file an action for injunctive relief and/or actual damages. Likewise, any property owner that believes that the provisions of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> have been violated shall have the right to file an action for injunctive relief and/or actual damages. Treble damages shall be awarded for a property owner's willful failure to comply with the payment obligations established under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>. In any action brought under <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite>, the court may award reasonable attorney's fees to any prevailing party.</text>
      </para>
      <para>
        <num>(b)</num>
        <text>Nothing herein shall be deemed to interfere with the right of a property owner to file an action against a tenant or non-tenant third party for the damage done to said owner's property. Nothing herein is intended to limit the damages recoverable by any party through a private action.</text>
      </para>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
    <section>
      <num>3.108.140</num>
      <heading>Severability.</heading>
      <text>If any provision of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> is held to be unconstitutional or otherwise invalid by any court of competent jurisdiction, the remaining provisions of <cite path="3.108">this chapter</cite> shall not be invalidated.</text>
      <annotations>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04773" path="§2">Ord. No. 04773, § 2, 2-14-2017</annotation>
        <annotation type="History" doc="County of San Mateo, Cal., Ord. No. 04795" path="§2">Ord. No. 04795, § 2, 2-27-2018</annotation>
      </annotations>
    </section>
  </container>
</container>
